<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?IS10744 arch
  name="SLlink-Oxygen"
  public-id="-//STEP//NOTATION SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  dtd-public-id="-//STEP//DTD SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  renamer-att="SLNames"
?><?ATTLINK table-block id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK table-block-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK chronology id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK res-institutes id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK political-profile-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK commodities id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnoteref slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK footnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK xr slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK anchor id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK intro-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group-content id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK is-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-table id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK directory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK article id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-overview id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK gen-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK essay id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK weights-and-measures id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK periodicals id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-table id "SLT"?><?Pub EntList AElig Aacute Abreve Acirc Agrave Amacr Aogon Aring Atilde Auml
 Cacute Ccaron Ccedil Ccirc Cdot Dagger Dstrok ETH Dcaron Eacute Ecaron Ecirc
 Egrave Emacr Eogon Euml Edot Gbreve Gcedil Gcirc Gdot Hcirc Iacute Icirc
 Idot Igrave Imacr Iogon Itilde Iuml Jcirc Lacute Lcaron Lstrok Nacute Ncaron
 Ntilde OElig Oacute Ocirc Ograve Omacr Oslash Otilde Ouml Racute Rcaron Sacute
 Scaron Scedil Scirc THORN Uacute Ubreve Ucirc Udblac Ugrave Umacr Uogon Uring
 Utilde Uuml Yacute Yuml Zacute Zcaron Zdot aacute abreve acirc aelig agrave
 amacr amp aogon aring atilde auml cacute ccaron ccedil ccirc cdot copy dagger
 deg dcaron dstrok eacute ecaron ecirc edot egrave emacr emsp ensp eogon eth
 euml euro frac12 frac13 frac14 frac34 frac23 gbreve gcirc gdot iacgr iacute
 icirc iexcl igrave imacr inodot itilde iuml lcaron ldquo lsquo lstrok mdash
 minus nacute nbsp ncaron ndash ntilde oacute ocirc odblac oelig ograve omacr
 oslash otilde ouml para racute rcaron rdquo rsquo sacute scaron scedil scirc
 sect tcedil thinsp thorn uacute ubreve?><COUNTRY-SURVEY
ORIGINAL-FILENAME="andchro.rtf"
ID="AD.CHRON"
ISO="ad"
ID-ROOT="ad"
USAGE="we"
PRINT-STYLE="PGWIDTH"
><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="gruard" fullname="Gruar, David"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="jobrien"
fullname="Jill O'Brien"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="gollann" fullname="Gollan, Nicola"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="tenzerj" fullname="Tenzer, Janine"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="LoveJ" fullname="Love, Juliet"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="Jonese" fullname="Jones, Eleanor"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="matthewsc" fullname="Matthews, Christopher"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="jlove" fullname="Juliet Love"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="lovej" fullname="Juliet Love"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="sandhyac" fullname="C, Sandhya"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="kmurison" fullname="Katy Murison"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="drees"
fullname="Donovan Rees"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="HartleyC" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><HEADING
>Chronology</HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="we"
TYPE="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE"
>Andorra</ALT-HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="we"
TYPE="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE"
>Chronology</ALT-HEADING><CHRON-LIST
><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="0768-01-01"
TO-DATE="0814-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>768&amp;ndash;814</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Reign of Charles &amp;lsquo;the Great&amp;rsquo;
(Charlemagne), the ruler of the Franks and the first Holy Roman Emperor. He
purportedly granted Andorra a charter guaranteeing its independence.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="0839-01-01"
TO-DATE="0839-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>839</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Act of Consecration of the cathedral in the
Spanish town of Urgell referred to the six parishes of Andorra&amp;mdash;the Count
of Urgell had assumed suzerainty over Andorra following the fracturing of
the Frankish realm.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1133-01-01"
TO-DATE="1133-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1133</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Count of
Urgell ceded the six parishes of Andorra to the Bishop of Urgell.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1159-01-01"
TO-DATE="1159-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1159</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Count of Foix, a French nobleman whose territory
included much of the Pyrenean region near Andorra, laid claim to the parishes;
he gained recognition of certain rights, but the dispute remained a source
of conflict.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1278-01-01"
TO-DATE="1278-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1278</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>A Pareatge (contract
or feudal agreement) was signed, sponsored by the King of Aragon, providing
for Andorran independence, under the joint sovereignty of the Count of Foix
and the Bishop of Urgell, who were to be paid tribute in alternate years.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1289-01-01"
TO-DATE="1289-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1288</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>A second Pareatge was signed, which
confirmed the agreement of 1278 and first referred to the sovereigns of Andorra
as the Copr&amp;iacute;nceps (Co-Princes).</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1419-01-01"
TO-DATE="1419-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1419</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Co-Princes granted an Andorran request for the formation of
a representative body for the debate of local issues; the Consell de la Terra
(Council of the Land, later the Consell General de les Valls d&amp;rsquo;Andorra&amp;mdash;General
Council of the Valleys of Andorra) comprised four members from each parish,
elected by the heads of the leading families in that parish.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1589-01-01"
TO-DATE="1589-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1589</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Henry of Bourbon, who had inherited the title
of Count of Foix, ascended the French throne as Henry IV; the French monarch,
therefore, became one of Andorra&amp;rsquo;s Co-Princes (Henry&amp;rsquo;s son and
successor, Louis XIII, reaffirmed Andorra&amp;rsquo;s status).</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1793-01-01"
TO-DATE="1793-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1793</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The proclamation of a republic in France left the
title of French Co-Prince unclaimed, provoking Andorran fears of subordination
to Spain.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1806-01-01"
TO-DATE="1806-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1806</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Napoleon Bonaparte, who had proclaimed
himself Emperor of France, issued a decree by which he assumed the title of
Co-Prince of Andorra.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1870-01-01"
TO-DATE="1870-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1870</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>With the final
restoration of a republic, the President of France became the French Co-Prince
of Andorra.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1912-01-01"
TO-DATE="1912-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1912</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Local defiance
of the episcopal Co-Prince was provoked by his attempt to ban the vital tobacco
trade.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1933-01-01"
TO-DATE="1933-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1933</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>A Russian &amp;eacute;migr&amp;eacute;, Boris
Skosirev, attempted to proclaim himself King Boris I of Andorra, with some
influential local support. The Bishop of Urgell sent troops to remove Skosirev
from the Principality and the General Council was dissolved by the Andorran
judicial authorities. The French Government subsequently sent forces to maintain
order and the General Council was re-established.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1970-01-01"
TO-DATE="1970-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1970</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Women&amp;rsquo;s suffrage was introduced; in the following
year the voting age was lowered from 25 to 21 years.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1978-01-01"
TO-DATE="1978-12-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>1978</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>A seventh parish, Escaldes-Engordany, was created
and the membership of the General Council was correspondingly expanded from
24 to 28.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1982-01-01"
TO-DATE="1982-01-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>January 1982</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>An executive body, known
as the Govern d&amp;rsquo;Andorra (Government of Andorra) was formed from within
the General Council, with Oscar Ribas Reig as Cap de Govern (Head of Government).</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1984-04-01"
TO-DATE="1984-04-30"
><CHRON-HEAD
>April 1984</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Ribas was forced to resign
upon the failure of his plan to introduce income tax. He was replaced in May
by Josep Pintat Solans.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1986-01-01"
TO-DATE="1986-01-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>January 1986</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Pintat
was re-elected to the post of Head of Government, following a general election
the previous month.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1990-01-01"
TO-DATE="1990-01-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>January 1990</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Following
a general election in December 1989, the General Council elected Ribas to
his second term as Head of Government.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
DATE="1993-05-04"
><CHRON-HEAD
>4 May 1993</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Andorra&amp;rsquo;s
first Constitution was promulgated, following its approval by 74.2% of those
participating in a referendum held in March. The Co-Princes remained nominally
sovereign, political parties and trade unions were legalized and proportional
representation was introduced for the election of 14 of the 28 members of
the General Council. Ambassadors were exchanged with France and Spain.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1993-07-01"
TO-DATE="1993-07-31"
><CHRON-HEAD
>28 July 1993</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Andorra was admitted to the United Nations.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
FROM-DATE="1994-11-01"
TO-DATE="1994-11-30"
><CHRON-HEAD
>November 1994</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Ribas&amp;rsquo; taxation and
budget proposals were defeated in the General Council and a motion of no confidence
in the Government was passed; Ribas resigned the premiership and was succeeded
by Marc Forn&amp;eacute; Moln&amp;eacute;, who formed a minority Government.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
DATE="1997-02-16"
><CHRON-HEAD
>16 February 1997</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>At a general election, Forn&amp;eacute;&amp;rsquo;s Uni&amp;oacute;
Liberal (UL&amp;mdash;Liberal Union) won 18 of the 28 seats in the General Council
and returned to power; Forn&amp;eacute; formed a new Government, with an increased
number of ministers and portfolios.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
DATE="2001-03-04"
><CHRON-HEAD
>4 March 2001</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Partit
Liberal d&amp;rsquo;Andorra (PLA&amp;mdash;Andorran Liberal Party, formerly the UL)
won 15 of the 28 seats in the General Council at a general election. Forn&amp;eacute;
was re-elected Head of Government by the Council.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>12 May 2003</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Joan Enric Vives
i Sic&amp;iacute;lia succeeded Joan Mart&amp;iacute; Alanis as the Bishop of Urgell
and episcopal Co-Prince.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
DATE="2005-04-24"
><CHRON-HEAD
>24 April 2005</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The PLA secured 14 seats
in the General Council, while the Partit Socialdem&amp;ograve;crata (PS&amp;mdash;Social
Democratic Party) won 12 and a coalition of two centrist parties took the
two remaining seats. A new PLA Government took office on 8 June under Albert
Pintat Santol&amp;agrave;ria.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>6 May 2007</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Nicolas Sarkozy succeeded Jacques Chirac
as President of the French Republic and French Co-Prince.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>26 April 2009</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>At the general
election the PS became the largest party in the General Council for the first
time, winning 14 of the 28 seats; the Coalici&amp;oacute; Reformista (CR&amp;mdash;Reformist
Coalition, led by the PLA) took 11 seats and Andorra pel Canvi (ApC&amp;mdash;Andorra
for Change) won three. Jaume Bartumeu Cassany, the leader of the PS, took
office as Head of Government on 5 June.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>16 December 2009</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>ApC announced that it
would not support the Government&amp;rsquo;s budget for 2010 in the General Council. </CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>3 April 2011</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>At a general election, prompted by the Government&amp;rsquo;s failure
to secure sufficient support for its budget, Dem&amp;ograve;crates per Andorra
(DA&amp;mdash;Democrats for Andorra, the successor alliance to the CR) won an
overwhelming majority, securing 20 seats in the General Council. The PS retained
just six seats, while the remaining two were won by a local conservative group,
the Uni&amp;oacute; Laurediana. Antoni Mart&amp;iacute; Petit, the leader of the DA,
was inaugurated as Head of Government on 12 May.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>30 June 2011</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Andorran
Government signed a formal monetary agreement with the European Union (EU),
which declared the euro to be Andorra&amp;rsquo;s official currency and permitted
the Principality to issue its own euro coins from 1 July 2013. (Owing to bureaucratic
delays, the introduction of the Andorran-minted euro was postponed.)</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>1 March 2015</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>At a general election the DA retained its majority in the General Council
with 15 seats. Liberals d&amp;rsquo;Andorra, a new grouping established by former
PLA members, secured eight seats, while a coalition between the PS, Greens
and independents won three, and newly formed Socialdemocr&amp;agrave;cia i Progr&amp;eacute;s
d&amp;rsquo;Andorra (Social Democracy and Progress) secured two. Mart&amp;iacute;
remained in office as Head of Government.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>11 March 2015</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Government assumed control
of Banca Privada d&amp;rsquo;Andorra (BPA), the Principality&amp;rsquo;s fourth largest
bank, following allegations by financial authorities in the USA that it had
been involved in money laundering activities. </CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>12 February 2016</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Government
signed an agreement with the EU that aimed to reduce tax evasion by allowing
the exchange of information on residents&amp;rsquo; financial assets and income.
The regulations came into force in 2018.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>14 May 2017</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Emmanuel Macron succeeded
Fran&amp;ccedil;ois Hollande as President of the French Republic and French Co-Prince.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>7 April 2019</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>At a general election the DA remained the largest party with 11
seats on the General Council, but failed to secure a majority. The PS and
Liberals d&amp;rsquo;Andorra won seven and four seats, respectively, and smaller
parties and independents won the remainder. Xavier Espot Zamora, former Minister
of Social Affairs, Justice and the Interior, took office as Head of Government
on 16 May.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>13 September
2019</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>French President Macron made an official visit
to Andorra, the first such visit since 2014.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>9 January 2020</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>Andorra formally requested
to join the International Monetary Fund.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>14 March 2020</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>The Government introduced
measures to contain the spread of the coronavirus disease COVID-19. </CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY><?Pub Caret?><CHRON-ENTRY
><CHRON-HEAD
>1 July 2022</CHRON-HEAD><CHRON-TEXT
>A new tourist tax came into force. The levy would be charged on
all foreign nationals staying in tourist accommodation in the country for
the first seven days of their stay.</CHRON-TEXT></CHRON-ENTRY></CHRON-LIST></COUNTRY-SURVEY>
