<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?IS10744 arch
  name="SLlink-Oxygen"
  public-id="-//STEP//NOTATION SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  dtd-public-id="-//STEP//DTD SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  renamer-att="SLNames"
?><?ATTLINK table-block id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK table-block-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK chronology id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK res-institutes id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK political-profile-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK commodities id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnoteref slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK footnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK xr slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK anchor id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK intro-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group-content id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK is-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-table id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK directory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK article id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-overview id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK gen-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK essay id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK weights-and-measures id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK periodicals id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-table id "SLT"?><?Pub EntList AElig Aacute Abreve Acirc Agrave Amacr Aogon Aring Atilde Auml
 Cacute Ccaron Ccedil Ccirc Cdot Dagger Dstrok ETH Dcaron Eacute Ecaron Ecirc
 Egrave Emacr Eogon Euml Edot Gbreve Gcedil Gcirc Gdot Hcirc Iacute Icirc
 Idot Igrave Imacr Iogon Itilde Iuml Jcirc Lacute Lcaron Lstrok Nacute Ncaron
 Ntilde OElig Oacute Ocirc Ograve Omacr Oslash Otilde Ouml Racute Rcaron Sacute
 Scaron Scedil Scirc THORN Uacute Ubreve Ucirc Udblac Ugrave Umacr Uogon Uring
 Utilde Uuml Yacute Yuml Zacute Zcaron Zdot aacute abreve acirc aelig agrave
 amacr amp aogon aring atilde auml cacute ccaron ccedil ccirc cdot copy dagger
 deg dcaron dstrok eacute ecaron ecirc edot egrave emacr emsp ensp eogon eth
 euml euro frac12 frac13 frac14 frac34 frac23 gbreve gcirc gdot iacgr iacute
 icirc iexcl igrave imacr inodot itilde iuml lcaron ldquo lsquo lstrok mdash
 minus nacute nbsp ncaron ndash ntilde oacute ocirc odblac oelig ograve omacr
 oslash otilde ouml para racute rcaron rdquo rsquo sacute scaron scedil scirc
 sect tcedil thinsp thorn uacute ubreve?><COUNTRY-SURVEY
ID="AF.EC"
ISO="af"
ID-ROOT="af"
USAGE="sasia"
SECT-TYPE="ECONOMY"
PRINT-STYLE="PGWIDTH"
><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="3"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="matthewsc"
fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="KhanMe" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="sandhyac" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="FrameI" fullname="FrameI"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="Main Computer"
fullname="BrowneV"?><HEADING
>Economy</HEADING><ALT-HEADING
TYPE="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE"
>Afghanistan</ALT-HEADING><ALT-HEADING
TYPE="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE"
>Economy</ALT-HEADING><AUTHOR-GROUP
><PRIMARY-AUTHORS
> <PERSON-NAME
><FORENAME
>Tirthankar</FORENAME><SURNAME
>Roy</SURNAME><REGNAL
>Professor in Economic History, Department of
Economic History, London School of Economics, London, United Kingdom</REGNAL></PERSON-NAME></PRIMARY-AUTHORS></AUTHOR-GROUP><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P1"
>Afghanistan has experienced war, <I
>coups d&amp;rsquo;&amp;eacute;tat</I>, state collapse and a shaky recovery in the
past 40 years&amp;mdash;and repeatedly in some cases. The after-effects of these
tragic episodes continue to be felt and have profoundly affected the process
of economic development in the country. The instability of the recent past
feeds pessimism about the economy and creates the impression that uncertainty
is intrinsic to the country&amp;rsquo;s history. It is tempting to conclude that
Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s turbulent politics somehow defines the region and that
it is this turbulence that has contributed to poverty, inequality and weak
economic growth in much of the country in recent times.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P2"
>However, as this essay will demonstrate,
this is not the case. Economics and politics have indeed been interdependent
in Afghanistan, as they are anywhere in the world. The 20th-century economic
history of Afg<?Pub Caret?>hanistan has a unique pattern, and that pattern
has influenced politics and economics in the region. The two features that
define the economic history of Afghanistan are resource poverty and the absence
of European colonial rule. These factors, however, were not exceptional to
Afghanistan. The two features appear in the histories of many poorer regions,
although they shaped the process of economic and political change in Afghanistan
with great force.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P3"
>During much of the 20th century,
Afghanistan was an agricultural country, but also a semi-arid, water-poor
country. Renewable water resources per capita in the country were less than
one-quarter of the global average in 2014. There are many water-poor countries
in the world. For example, India, Pakistan and Bangladesh are even more water-poor
than Afghanistan by this benchmark, but those three countries have access
to the sea, maritime trade, port cities, irrigable deltas and river valleys,
and these resources have sustained industry, commerce, finance and fiscally
stable states. As Afghanistan is landlocked, its economy has diversified less
than those of its neighbours. Although it does have mineral resources, these
are largely untapped. This resource poverty, coupled with the country&amp;rsquo;s
climate and geography, has made for only small taxable capacity and left states
militarily weak, giving rise to states and empires that have relied heavily
on the loyalty of local chiefs and warlords. The military-fiscal capacity
of the state in Afghanistan is limited too, and this has had similar consequences. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P4"
>The South Asian mainland had many
polities in the 18th century that fit this pattern. The British Empire that
emerged from the end of the 18th century altered the situation in South Asia
substantially. This brings attention to the second of the two features: the
difference that European colonialism could make to the political economy of
the South Asian region. By cutting out warlords from the tax system and by
raising a standing army, the British Raj ruling India could centralize power
sufficiently to impose a degree of political unification and economic integration,
the likes of which the region had never seen before. The Empire did not set
out to reform or to develop India. Still, being a commercially minded and
European-origin state, the United Kingdom&amp;rsquo;s rule had the effect of weakening
traditional institutions and influences, including caste and feudal loyalties.
Foreign rule created a state significantly less dependent on local warlords
and landlords than any state that ruled this land before the British arrived
in the region.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P5"
>This external force was missing
in Afghanistan. Although often caught up in military contests between Russia
and the Western powers, and often forced to cede territories to both, Afghanistan&amp;mdash;like
Iran, Saudi Arabia and Thailand&amp;mdash;has never been colonized. Because Afghanistan
was not conquered, indigenous economic and political institutions survived
in this region more than these did in, for example, the rest of South Asia.
And because Afghanistan was resource-poor, the Governments running the country
from the capital, Kabul, could never impose their writ over the entire country.
Owing to their oil resources, the central authorities in Iran or Saudi Arabia
could achieve much greater control over the provinces and local elites&amp;mdash;an
option that was not available to the Afghan state.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P6"
>These two features&amp;mdash;resource
poverty and a weak centre&amp;mdash;have made economic development a troubled
process throughout Afghan history. Any state-led or managed development programme
would need a robust federal set-up. The country did not have such a structure
and could not easily create one without running into conflicts, even civil
war. Therefore, planned and top-down economic modernization policies have
often gone badly and raised tensions between the centre and the regions. The
past 40 years or so of conflicts are a result of many factors, including the
Cold War and geopolitical tensions. The fundamental structural element&amp;mdash;a
perennial tension between centralization of power and fragmented power&amp;mdash;was
one of those features. Resource poverty made the centre relatively weak, and
the task of managed economic transformation much harder than otherwise. This,
in summary, is the central story of economic change in Afghanistan. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P7"
>This essay will present a chronological
narrative of economic change. As is suggested above, this story cannot be
told by disengaging it from the politics of the country, as the two dimensions
are often interlinked, but the focus will be on economic change and economic
development in the country.</P><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Emergence of Modern Afghanistan</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P8"
>Afghanistan is predominantly rural
and agricultural, with only a small urban population. The main livelihoods
are farming and pastoralism. A century ago in Afghanistan the average peasant
was poor, indebted and exposed to the risk of droughts. Agriculture produced
enough for the local population to subsist on but was not a path to accumulating
wealth. Because water for irrigation was available locally in only a few regions,
the average plot of land did not produce much. In large swathes of the country
and especially outside the three main river basins, agriculture provided at
best a precarious form of subsistence living. As geography did not change,
the majority of the population living on the land a century ago would have
lived in the same way that they had done in centuries past.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P9"
>About the same size as France, Afghanistan
is thinly populated. A reliable census was not conducted until the 1980s.
Rough estimates suggest that the population was about 12m. in the early 20th
century and remained at about that level until as late as the 1970s. The death
rate was very high throughout, matched by a high birth rate. The exact numbers
for these indicators are not available, but the plausible scenario of demographic
inertia reinforces the impression of inertia in livelihoods. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P10"
>The picture of immobility needs
to be balanced by dramatic movements in the political arena. The major Afghan
towns emerged as seats of political power and centres of commerce and crafts
sustained by the wealth of the urban elite. However, groups that ruled the
provinces insisted on autonomy, among other reasons, to ensure that their
hold over the limited natural resources (such as arable land and pastures)
remained secure from outsiders. With limited tax resources and a dependence
on regional ethnic groups, the powers that ruled Kabul had neither the military
might nor the economic influence to establish their writ over the entire country.
Therefore, political integration was far too difficult a challenge for regimes
to take on.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P11"
>Although Afghanistan was never
colonized in a formal sense, British power played a fundamental role in Afghanistan's
emergence as a country. In the early 18th century the region did not form
one nation or empire. There were three distinct political spaces. Herat and
Qandahar in the south and south-west were under Persian influence; Kabul,
Ghazni and Jalalabad in the east were under Mughal imperial influence; and
the regions in the north were under Central Asian suzerainty. The conquests
of Nader Shah (1688&amp;ndash;1747), a warlord of Khorasan, and his successor,
Ahmad Shah Abdali (1722&amp;ndash;72), brought these regions under a single military
command. Kabul became the summer capital of the Durrani Empire (as Afghanistan
was then known) in 1776.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P12"
>There was little regional integration
in government. In fact, the opposite was the case. In exchange for a promise
of loyalty, groups and tribal councils that controlled the regions were left
in effect autonomous. The formation of a dominant centre sealed their autonomy.
Primitive roads and communications ensured that long-distance cross-border
trade was confined to a few cities and trading routes. The regions retained
their livelihoods that were dependent on local natural resources. The broad
tribal divisions followed the earlier pattern of regionalization: Turkic groups
in the north, Tajiks and Persian-speaking groups in the west, and the Afghans
or Pashtuns in the east and the centre of the country.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P13"
>In 1823 the Sikh king Ranjit Singh
captured the eastern territories of the Emirate of Afghanistan (as it had
become in that year under Dost Mohammad Khan), while chaos and infighting
had weakened the Empire itself. Between 1838 and 1879 the British officials
who were based in India interfered deeply in Afghan politics. More than the
desire to possess territories, a desire to fix the border between British
India and imperial Russia drove the Anglo-Afghan conflict. The British fought
two wars in Afghanistan (1839&amp;ndash;42 and 1878&amp;ndash;80), demarcated the
boundaries between British India and Afghanistan and eventually came to control
Afghan foreign affairs. In effect Afghanistan became a British protectorate
and its modern borders drawn were drawn by an external power. Beyond these
steps, the British Empire had little effect on or interest in the country.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P14"
>The protectorate ended after the
Third Anglo-Afghan war, which took place in 1919. The war was an unusual conflict,
in that it helped both protagonists to achieve their objectives. Following
the end of the conflict in August, the Afghan emir Amanullah Khan wrested
control of foreign affairs and declared full independence, and the British
negotiated an agreement that defined the land border between Afghanistan and
British India. As a military conflict, the war was a small affair, with more
losses on the Afghan side. The First World War had just ended, and the British
had little appetite for another long battle. The newly formed Union of Soviet
Socialist Republics (USSR) took a strong pro-independence position in support
of Amanullah&amp;rsquo;s demands, and an independent Afghanistan was considered
by British India to be a better potential ally than a hostile and discontented
colony. The de facto independence of Afghanistan brought the king face to
face with the task of building a country and its economy.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>1919&amp;ndash;45: The Beginnings of Development Projects</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P15"
>From the beginning of the reign
of Amanullah Khan in 1919, when a modernization programme commenced, the fractured
polity placed the regime in a dilemma. Any countrywide development project
would require political centralization&amp;mdash;a move that the regions might
not want to be a part of. However, if the modernization project did succeed
in the areas where favourable conditions existed, that would widen the inequality
between the capital city and surrounding areas and the countryside, even between
tribes, adding to political discontent.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P16"
>Khan was a hawk on modernization.
His policy on modernization included drawing more women into public life and
relied on a broadly Francophile cosmopolitanism in Kabul. However, he failed
in his effort to extend this policy outside the city. He could not get the
regional chiefs on board. The Pashtun and Pashtun-influenced areas had a system
of periodic meetings of tribal chiefs, known as a <I
>jirga</I> (a grand council).
In times of national crisis, Afghan kings would invite members of the royal
family, tribal chiefs and religious leaders to a jirga in the capital. It
is not clear how institutionalized or rule-bound these councils were, but
they were a distant parallel to a legislative body. Amanullah, whose grandfather
had once called the grand council for political reasons, wanted to turn this
council into a permanent legislative body and secure agreement on his more
ambitious plans. However, this move failed.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P17"
>Amanullah's reign was cut short
in 1929, following the rebellion of the Tajik military commander Habibullah
Kalakani (also known as Baccha-i-Saqao&amp;mdash;Son of the Water Carrier). In
popular memory, Kalakani is said to have opposed Khan&amp;rsquo;s secularism.
Seen from another angle, Kalakani's opposition had more to do with opportunism
than ideology. In any case, Kalakani's was one of a series of regional and
tribal movements to follow, which underscored the military weakness of the
government and its precarious hold on the regions.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P18"
>In 1929 the &amp;lsquo;Musahiban&amp;rsquo;
brothers, from the line of the &amp;lsquo;Peshawar Sirdars&amp;rsquo;, raised a tribal
force and invaded Afghanistan from British India. The Musahiban dynasty remained
in power until 1973 and continued the economic modernization programme. During
the short-lived reign of Muhammad Nadir Shah (1929&amp;ndash;33), the regime adopted
a constitutional monarchy system. The Constitution was meant to be an instrument
for political integration, with a parliament based on the tribal council model,
which would endorse the programmes for centralized reforms. Again, these moves
failed. With the bureaucracy controlled by the court, the legislature had
limited room for manoeuvre. This situation did not satisfy the regional leaders,
and there was no real democracy in Afghanistan. From this point on and for
several decades to come, the absence of political party-based democracy made
securing agreement on the Constitution an almost impossible task.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P19"
>At the same time, the economic
modernization programme was changing Kabul in radical ways. The Government
opened its doors to Western experts and advisers. In 1932 Kabul University
was established. A programme for mass and technical education had been under
way for some time, again with the help of foreign experts. In 1933 the central
bank, Bank-e-Millie was established. In 1939&amp;mdash;a few years into Mohammad
Zahir Shah&amp;rsquo;s reign (1933&amp;ndash;73)&amp;mdash;government ministers and advisers
initiated an industrialization-cum-modernization programme.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P20"
>The obstacles were significant.
Electricity needed to be produced on a large scale, machines for modern industry
had to be imported, finance was expensive and managerial skills non-existent,
and there were few large private enterprises to take the lead. A group of
European and US engineering firms had claimed that the untapped waters of
the Hindu Kush rivers could be used for hydro-electric power. In the revival
of trade following the economic depression of the 1930s, it was easy and cheap
to procure machines from abroad, and in several crafts&amp;mdash;brickmaking,
metal products and woodworking&amp;mdash;there was a wealth of well-developed
manual skills and knowledge of raw and manufactured materials.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P21"
>The programme soon ran into trouble
as the Second World War broke out in 1939. The supply of machines stalled,
and shortages developed in essential supplies, diverting the Afghan Government&amp;rsquo;s
attention elsewhere. The Government and the central bank managed a difficult
situation and saved most industrial, utility and services firms by buying
up share capital. As economic reconstruction began, new challenges emerged.
Floods had destroyed some of the building projects undertaken before the war,
and US technology in infrastructure projects did not always work. For example,
foreign-supplied explosives did not work very well in rock-sand formations.
Furthermore &amp;lsquo;the Afghans&amp;rsquo; working habits and their different valuation
of human and material resources&amp;nbsp;...&amp;nbsp;overtaxed even American organizational
ability&amp;rsquo;, according to Peter G.&amp;nbsp;Franck, a consultant to US firms
working in Afghanistan following the war. In Franck&amp;rsquo;s assessment, political
disintegration posed the biggest risk to Afghanistan's economic development
project.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P22"
>The end of the Second World War
in 1945 and the Partition of British India into two countries in 1947 created
other problems. Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s foreign policy now needed to engage with
Pakistan, which wanted to create a strong federation by incorporating the
Afghan semi-autonomous groups living on Pakistani territory. The Government
in Afghanistan favoured an openly &amp;lsquo;irredentist&amp;rsquo; ideology to advocate
a return to autonomy for the Pashtun-speaking groups in Pakistan. The relationship
between Afghanistan and its newly independent Muslim neighbour had got off
to a difficult start.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P23"
>However, as peace returned, a paradigm
shift in economic development was taking shape in the 1950s.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>1950&amp;ndash;78: The Rise and Fall of the Modernization Paradigm</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P24"
>In part, the paradigm was just
another form of the modernization project that had begun in the 1920s, but
it was also deeply influenced by economic changes happening in the rest of
South Asia. In 1960 the Minister of Foreign Affairs, Mohammad Naim Khan, articulated
the sentiment: &amp;lsquo;we do aspire to catch up to our neighbors; because failing
this, Afghanistan will probably disappear. It will be overwhelmed by the sheer
rate of advancement of its neighbors&amp;rsquo;.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P25"
>As in the rest of the region, the
court and government ministers thought that the state should get involved
in the economic development process. Moreover, Afghan political leaders understood
that the country needed to keep its borders open to capital and skills from
abroad. Skills shortages were a critical obstacle, not least because the state
had more limited capacity in Afghanistan than in, for example, Pakistan or
India. In almost every country in South Asia, the 1950s was an era of economic
planning, and Afghanistan was no different. But whereas India&amp;rsquo;s 1956
five-year plan made industrialization the aim before development policy, Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s
counterpart made infrastructure the goal, rather like in Pakistan and Nepal.
The presence of an indigenous business class in India and a bigger capacity
to capture tax and international aid set it apart. Afghanistan lacked these
initial conditions for industrialization.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P26"
>The most important field of public
investment was the multi-purpose river valley project. Afghanistan has three
major river basins: the Amu Darya basin in the north, the Indus basin in the
east and the Helmand basin in the south. The Helmand Valley project began
in 1939 as an Afghan-US collaboration but did not deliver many benefits. The
Nangarhar region on the borders of Afghanistan and Pakistan is fed by the
Kabul and the Kunar rivers and has some of the most fertile agricultural tracts
in the country. This area was also historically the core commercial zone.
Its relatively easy transport access to Pakistan made for a lot of trade between
the two countries, centred in the Afghan city of Jalalabad. Irrigation in
Nangarhar was a focus of Soviet-Afghan collaboration. And finally, regarding
the Amu Darya river (formerly known as the Oxus), water resources concerned
both the USSR and Afghanistan more directly, as they shared the basin. Again,
ambitious plans emerged to develop the water resources of the basin, although
not much progress was made. A second significant area of investment was roads,
built mainly with US collaboration. Major highways linking Afghan cities were
constructed in the 1960s. These projects stimulated internal trade, as well
as trade with Afghanistan's neighbours.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P27"
>Sustaining the impetus for development
was a difficult challenge, as financing a development plan that relied heavily
on imports was a problem. To pay for concessional loans taken out for these
projects, Afghanistan entered into trade collaboration with the USSR based
on a system of barter. The roads and irrigation projects stimulated the production
of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s main export goods. But the basket of goods was a limited
one, confined to cotton, wool, dried fruit and karakul skin. With the internal
market still fairly small, foreign investors took little interest in the country.
Beyond exports and trade in local produce, private enterprise had limited
room for growth. The Government's capacity fell short of the promises that
it had made, and progress was perpetually constrained by poor takings, bureaucratic
corruption and the resistance of regional leaders.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P28"
>The 1960s saw the beginning of
the end of the uneasy equilibrium that had existed between modernizing Kabul
and the semi-autonomous countryside. On the political level, despite the weakness
of the political party system, democracy was taking root. Several parliamentary
seats were open to elections. Student movements in 1965 and 1969&amp;ndash;70
and elections in 1971 became occasions when popular political sentiment found
a platform for expression&amp;mdash;and the results did not favour the ruling
classes.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P29"
>On the economic plane, three significant
developments would deliver results in the next decade. First, Green Revolution
agricultural technology and farm mechanization altered the pattern of inequality
in parts of the countryside, from a political sort of hierarchy cemented by
clan loyalty towards less acceptable forms of economic inequality. In the
1970s, when reliable statistics on land tenure began to be available, a large
proportion (40% or more) of the rural population was landless. In the northern
regions, a tiny elite owned much of the land. Poverty and inequality now began
to reshape the discourse of development in Afghanistan, by creating room for
a Marxist agrarian reform programme, which promised regulation of credit markets
and the redistribution of land.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P30"
>The second development was that
the radical left made significant inroads among university students, and as
the formation of political parties became possible, trained some of the more
successful individuals to influence the nascent parties. The growth of the
left-wing movement made the US-dependent modernization project less popular
than it once was. By the mid-1970s the open doors policy towards the West
was nearing its end.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P31"
>Third and finally, the USSR was
becoming closely involved with foreign policy, security infrastructure and
developmental ideology. A <I
>coup d&amp;rsquo;&amp;eacute;tat</I> in 1978 brought
a coalition of military officers and the pro-Soviet radical left to power.
The modernizing impulse continued, but now took on a Soviet face. Soviet engineers
replaced US technicians, and military experts from the USSR visited Afghanistan
frequently. Through these links, the Soviet Government kept itself informed
of the internal politics of the new regime in Kabul. The USSR was anxious
about the country&amp;rsquo;s foreign policy mainly because stability in Kabul
was a key factor in the stability of the Central Asian Soviet republics, with
which Afghanistan shared a border of some 1,250&amp;nbsp;km. Ethnic groups that
did not feel any reason to commit either to socialism or Kabul-style economic
modernization straddled the border. This was not Cold War politics for the
USSR; it was bound more by geopolitical considerations than global military
rivalry. But because the USSR was involved, the USA and Pakistan became increasingly
concerned by the recent developments. As a result, Afghanistan was fast turning
into a new arena in which the Cold War would play out.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P32"
>The socialist turn served Afghanistan
badly. A socialist economic system would mean more centralization and not
less. The country had neither the fiscal nor the military means to carry out
such a project. Politically, the rise of the left in Kabul underscored the
distance between the city and the regions, and the appointment of overbearing
left-wing officials to key positions angered and upset regional Afghan leaders.
The pronounced pro-USSR bias of Afghan radicalism and dissension within its
ranks did not help matters, as well as alarming US officials.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P33"
>The main economic reform programme&amp;mdash;a
land redistribution project&amp;mdash;made only stumbling progress. The land was
of poor quality, by and large. The officials had little detailed knowledge
of who owned which land: &amp;lsquo;It has proved more difficult to separate khans
and landlords from peasants than Marxist analysis had predicted&amp;rsquo;, according
to the academics Nancy Newell and Richard Newell in 1979. The move raised
concerns over its consequences for the ethnic balance of power. The USSR was
an ally of the Afghan communists, but this friendship pleased almost nobody
else. There were many reasons for the animosity. Ideological differences were
not the most important of these. One perennial problem was water-sharing arrangements
in the Amu Darya basin. The USSR often acted like a bully in the negotiations;
its principal commitment was to the Soviet republics of Turkmenistan and Uzbekistan
and not to Afghanistan. With 27% of the annual flow in its territory, Afghanistan
had access to just 7% of the water of the river, according to the Tashkent
Agreement of 1987.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P34"
>From late 1978 clashes between
the Afghan Government and local communities erupted in many areas. In 1979
even Afghan cities were living in a state of insecurity. Several powerful
militaristic opposition groups emerged to resist central rule. Most professed
loyalty to the tenets of Islam, but among them there were considerable differences
over the mix between secularism and religious sentiment. Thus began the Afghan
civil war, which would last for the next quarter of a century.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>1979&amp;ndash;2001: Civil War and State Collapse</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P35"
>The USSR&amp;rsquo;s military and security
apparatus became committed to sustaining Afghanistan from early 1979, as the
regime threatened to collapse under the weight of infighting and a divided
military. The defeated Soviet army withdrew in 1989. In 1996 a little-known
movement known as the Taliban overthrew a dysfunctional coalition Government
and established Islamist rule. Civil war conditions had destroyed a great
deal of the infrastructure that had been built in the pre-1978 era, killed
between 500,000 and 2m. Afghan citizens, left vast areas littered with unexploded
landmines and forced several million people to seek refuge in neighbouring
countries and beyond. Aid from the USA, Saudi Arabia, the People's Republic
of China and Iran had sustained the rebel groups in their war against the
Soviet military. Afghanistan's precarious economy was devastated, although
few estimates exist of the nature and extent of the loss to income and property.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P36"
>Seeing the crucial period from
1978 until the mid-1990s in Afghan history as a featureless decline would
be a mistake, however. Between 1978 and 1994 Afghan cities, especially Kabul,
continued to benefit from Soviet, then Russian, contact. One measure of the
gain was the large number of women who received higher and technical education
in the USSR and returned to occupy key administrative positions. When the
coalition Government fell in 1996, these women&amp;mdash;and female education
and employment more broadly&amp;mdash;came under attack from the fiercely conservative
Taliban. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P37"
>None of the foreign powers appeared
to realize nor care about the fact that the Taliban embodied an extreme form
of Islamic fundamentalism, which had been nurtured in the North-West Frontier
Province of Pakistan, where the Taliban had their base and where the conservative
Deobandi <I
>ulema</I> (religious scholars) had an entrenched position in educational
and cultural life. Most Taliban leaders were products of these theological
seminaries. Despite an allegiance to Islam and frequent denial that the movement
was ethnically biased, the Pashtun dominance of the movement pitted the Pashtun
against the other major ethnic groups.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P38"
>By 1998 the movement had divided
up between the mainly Pashtun Taliban, and the Mujahidins formed of Tajik
and Uzbek ethnic groups. Pakistan supported the former with aid and military
help, whereas the Russian Federation, Iran and the Central Asian republics
supported the latter. The USA remained neutral until 1998 but then joined
the attack against the Taliban. The US Administration had two major grievances.
After the bombing of two US embassies in Africa in 1998, the instigator of
the attacks, Osama Bin Laden, had taken refuge in Afghanistan; and poppy cultivation
had greatly expanded in the Nangarhar region, giving a huge boost to heroin
production and global trade, particularly in the USA. Almost all of the poppies
were grown in Taliban-controlled areas, and the regime earned substantial
revenue by taxing the production and encouraging the trade.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P39"
>Afghanistan's old problems&amp;mdash;weak
state capacity and political fragmentation&amp;mdash;had returned during the Taliban
era to disable the regime and made it a weak force for economic change of
any kind. Political fragmentation returned with a vengeance because the revolutionaries
were divided and had carved their territories of influence and control from
the 1980s. After the Taliban's rise to power, the United Front (also known
as the Northern Alliance&amp;mdash;a coalition of opposition groups based in the
north of the country) controlled about 10% of Afghanistan's land area. It
was this coalition that took over when, in October 2001, in the month following
terrorist attacks on the USA by al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida, which had been given refuge
by the Taliban, US military forces invaded Afghanistan and ousted the Taliban. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P40"
>Although reliable national income
data are not available for Afghanistan in the 1980s and 1990s, demographic
statistics show that these two decades were a &amp;lsquo;lost&amp;rsquo; era economically.
Afghanistan had one of the highest birth rates in the world (47&amp;ndash;54 births
per 1,000 people annually in 1980&amp;ndash;99) and one of the highest infant
mortality rates in the world (147&amp;ndash;191 children died before the age of
five years per 1,000 live births). With only patchy data available, it is
impossible to say whether the infant mortality rate increased during this
turbulent period. If it did, this would testify to a collapse of the health
care system in the countryside. Life expectancy at birth was only 39&amp;ndash;45
years at this time, and Afghanistan was losing a big part of its working-age
population to migration.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P41"
>Health care suffered a particularly
heavy blow from the political turmoil. This setback was not due entirely to
the limited financial capacity of the state. Taliban ascendancy prompted heavy
migration. Some of the most skilled workers left early and resettled successfully.
Among those leaving were many doctors and nurses who went to Western European
and North American countries. Furthermore, Taliban policy to segregate women
and remove them from the workforce meant that female medical professionals
were forbidden from studying medicine and practising. That policy had a devastating
impact on maternal health care and contributed to keeping total fertility
rates at a high level (7&amp;ndash;8 children per woman on average).</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P42"
>The end of Taliban rule in 2001
and the emergence of a new regime came with the promise of a significant turnaround
in the demographic characteristics of the country. The revival of the public
health care system and the return of women to the workforce happened almost
immediately, with far-reaching effects. It was a shaky process none the less.
The earlier period of high fertility meant that by the 2010s the country had
a large population of young men and women seeking jobs. In some assessments
many working-age young people who were unable to find productive work took
up arms, either on the Government&amp;rsquo;s side or the insurgents, thus keeping
the conflict alive. This is an overly pessimistic assessment, but it does
underscore how delicately balanced the economic recovery process was.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>2002&amp;ndash;13: Turnaround</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P43"
>The past two decades in the economic
history of Afghanistan can be divided into two parts: the first phase was
characterized by dynamism, and in the second phase some of the initial gains
made in the first phase were lost as the country descended back into a civil
war.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P44"
>After the initial recovery from
the civil war of 1996&amp;ndash;2001, the new Government set out to make investments
again. A significant part of that money came from Western and other donors
and funded the construction of new infrastructure. A vast number of jobs were
created in the public sector, mainly in the security services. Trade revived,
and investment in canals and dams increased. Above all, a substantial amount
of money and energy were diverted to public health care, education and agriculture. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P45"
>Health care was a priority area&amp;mdash;and
the one that registered the most gains in a short time. The success of health
care reconstruction demonstrated that money alone was not the critical factor
in the recovery process. Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s open borders to skilled people
were an attraction for several non-governmental organizations (NGO) based
in India and Pakistan to establish hospitals there. The new facilities employed
Indians and Pakistanis, as well as Afghans who had been trained abroad, and
Russian doctors and nurses. As well as treating diseases, the new infrastructure
significantly improved immunization systems, which brought some infectious
diseases under control. Safer water and sanitation projects also improved
the quality of life for many Afghan citizens.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P46"
>Education was another priority
and another area of success. In just a few years, more than one-half of the
school-age population had enrolled in schools and pursued a uniform national
curriculum. About one-third of them were girls, which was a striking development,
as girls&amp;rsquo; enrolment in educational establishments had fallen to zero
in Taliban-controlled areas. NGOs and government agencies campaigned successfully
for increased enrolment, with positive results.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P47"
>The demographic turnaround was
a dramatic one. Between 2000 and 2019 the population increased from some 22m.
to about 31m.&amp;mdash;an annual average growth rate of about 2%. Life expectancy
at birth improved from 45 years to about 65 years. During that time the infant
mortality rate fell from 147 per 1,000 live births to just above 60. Net migration
was still negative and high in the earlier years of the recovery but dropped
sharply in the later years. These data suggest the prospect of a population
explosion, which resource poverty and civil war conditions could make an impossible
challenge for any government to deal with. The good news is that during these
two decades the total fertility rate fell so sharply (from about 8 children
per woman to 4.8 children) that the population growth rate also began to decline.
Throughout this period Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s ranking in the United Nations (UN)
Development Programme&amp;rsquo;s Human Development Index and individual measures
of health and nutritional status and education improved. Meanwhile, access
to water and electricity grew at unprecedented rates.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P48"
>There were other positive changes
during the two decades of recovery. Work began on major river valley projects,
especially in the upper Amu Darya basin. The urbanization rate accelerated.
Urbanization rates reflected increased natural population growth in the cities,
thanks to a higher survival rate among infants. There was also migration into
the towns for employment and education. Much of that flow remained Kabul-bound.
The gap between Kabul and the second-largest city, Qandahar, widened rapidly,
even as migration added pressure to public services in Kabul. Overall, the
quality of life was significantly better in the cities compared with the rural
areas. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P49"
>The initial burst of expenditure
produced a healthy growth rate of real national income too. South Asia is
a good benchmark to compare Afghanistan with. Between 2004 and 2013 the average
Afghan income as a proportion of South Asian average income increased from
35% to 44%, and as a percentage of global average income from 10% to 14%.
This progress is significant because in 2002, when data for gross domestic
product (GDP) in Afghanistan were first compiled, it was the poorest country
in South Asia. The high growth rate for the next eight years showed not only
that the funding from foreign donors helped, but also that increasing economic
integration through trade, migration and investment in one of the world&amp;rsquo;s
fastest-growing regions produced a dramatic outcome in the country. However,
this relative gain disappeared in the following years, and by 2019 average
Afghan income was again only 35% of the South Asian average.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>2013&amp;ndash;: Reversal</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P50"
>The fact that Afghanistan was falling
behind its peers in terms of economic growth was significant. It revealed
the three pitfalls in the process of recovery. A part of the regression was
clearly due to the drawdown of international military forces on Afghan soil
between 2012 and 2014 and a drop in related investment and expenditure. However,
there were also deeper structural problems that the recession of the subsequent
five years had revealed more starkly.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P51"
>First, despite all the help from
its security partners, the Afghan Government remained too weak to integrate
the regions under centralized rule. About 40% of the land area remained outside
the regime&amp;rsquo;s control. Here, opium cultivation and drug trafficking continued
unchecked. &amp;lsquo;Over the course of reconstruction, the reports of international
organizations and NGOs were replete with tales of health-related programs
that had to be suspended, cancelled, postponed, or significantly scaled back
because of security issues&amp;rsquo;, according to Jones <I
>et al</I> (2006;
see <I
>Bibliography</I>).</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P52"
>Second, the economy did not, and
could not, diversify enough. Given the resources poverty of the country, agricultural
and industrial development were not sustainable avenues of economic development.
The insurgency restricted the growth of services subsectors such as tourism
and left a vast army of unemployed youth with insufficient training for other
forms of employment. The public sector remained a large employer. Trade, finance
and other commercial services boomed, but the ability of these services to
generate more and well-paid jobs depended on there being strong production
sectors. Overall, economic growth in Afghanistan was services-based, as in
the rest of South Asia. However, most services jobs were low-paid and insecure,
except those in the government sector. Even then, it was reported that the
government paid its soldiers less than did some insurgent groups to their
members.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P53"
>Third and finally, poverty remained
entrenched, and inequality was on the rise. As on many occasions in the past,
robust economic growth was centred in the cities and the fertile agricultural
areas, leaving the resource-poor countryside behind. Inequality between the
countryside and the towns grew wider. In urban areas, &amp;lsquo;eight out of
ten households had access to improved sanitation in 2013&amp;minus;14, compared
to only three out of ten in rural households&amp;rsquo;, according to the World
Bank in 2017.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P54"
>Economic growth bypassed the rural
poor, and the insurgency hurt them the most. &amp;lsquo;The poorest and most vulnerable
segments of the population benefited least from [the] growth, and the same
groups suffered the most once the economy and the security condition deteriorated&amp;rsquo;,
according to a report on poverty published in 2017. UN estimates suggest that
personal income inequality has risen significantly since 2002, which is a
trend common to all countries in South Asia.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P55"
>Part of the inequality problem
stemmed from a high rate of unemployment. The end of the civil wars and the
initial investment in health care paid off in rising population growth, but
this added further pressure to the job market and public services. Youth unemployment
was at unsustainable levels in the country. In 2013&amp;minus;14, when the withdrawal
of international armed forces was at its peak, unemployment rose, and &amp;lsquo;one
in every four people participating in the labor market were either working
for less than eight hours per week or do not have a job and are actively looking
for one&amp;rsquo;, according to the World Bank in 2017.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P56"
>Some of the disruptions caused
by the shock of NATO troop withdrawals in 2014 wore off over the next five
years. According to World Bank statistics, Afghan GDP did not grow after 2015.
Aid dependency levels increased. Increased in-migration of former refugees
from Iran and Pakistan added to the stress, and even intensified conflicts
in some areas. The return of insurgency had a curious effect. As new foreign
insurgent groups took advantage of the stress, the Taliban, now under a different
and reportedly more moderate leadership, became defensive and willing to strike
a deal with the USA. In February 2020 the deal finally materialized.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P57"
>From early 2021 the outcome of
the peace process was, in fact, an unleashing of further conflict. Foreign
forces present in Afghanistan dwindled to insignificant numbers, with the
USA hastening its withdrawal of forces and other NATO countries following
suit (see History), but that number was still vital to secure some semblance
of stability in the capital. Taliban forces battled government troops and
made significant advances. Civilian casualties ran into thousands, nearly
one-half of them being women and children. The threat of a third front in
the ongoing civil war&amp;mdash;against Islamic State Khorasan Province, the Afghan
branch of Islamic State (IS)&amp;mdash;emerged. Against this backdrop, the Afghan
Government, weighed down by corruption, propped up by foreign aid and still
unable to pay civil servants, teetered on the brink of collapse. </P><P
>The coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic from early 2020 hit the economy
hard. Compared with the rest of South Asia, the expected drop in national
income due to working time lost was estimated to be smaller in Afghanistan,
simply because industry and services were not doing that well before the crisis
and agriculture was on the road to recovery from a drought in 2018. However,
amid high unemployment and a tense security situation, any recession had the
potential to generate further conflict.</P><P
>In August 2021 the Taliban reoccupied Kabul, following the hurried exit
of international forces. The dramatic growth in the Afghan economy during
most of the 20-year interregnum between the two Taliban regimes was due to
significant investment from abroad, a business-friendly Government and gender
equality in employment, especially in the service sector. It was also heavily
funded by aid, particularly infrastructural developments and the military.
At the time of the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s return, foreign aid formed about 40% percent
of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s GDP. The handling of this aid involved extensive corruption,
as alleged by both friends and critics of the Government. The mismanagement
of the economy reached damaging levels in the last four years of the elected
Government, when national income stopped growing. Arguably, this mismanagement
and the country&amp;rsquo;s impending economic collapse precipitated the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s
military success.</P><P
>Foreign money had enabled the central bank to build a substantial reserve,
most of it held in the USA. With an impending change of regime, Western Governments
suspended aid to Afghanistan, the World Bank and the International Monetary
Fund (IMF) halted assistance, and the USA froze the country&amp;rsquo;s foreign
reserves, with a significant proportion later ring-fenced to compensate the
victims of the 11 September 2011 terrorist attacks (given that many terrorism-related
lawsuits against the Taliban are pending in the US courts). Media reports
suggest that restoring freedom to women (who have been prohibited from most
jobs after the Taliban takeover) and girls (who have been denied access to
secondary education) was also a condition for releasing the reserves.</P><P
>The crisis on the external accounts spilled over into a banking and fiscal
crisis. Banks restricted their business. A sharp contraction in government
spending reduced demand and worsened unemployment. The currency, the Afghani,
fell sharply against the US dollar, and with employment in disarray, there
were reports of hunger and hardship. Imports fell sharply, damaging consumption
and investment. Thousands of highly skilled workers fled abroad. The reimposition
of sanctions stopped remittance inflows from abroad, a substantial 4% of the
national economy before the transition.</P><P
>The crisis eased somewhat by February 2022. The new Government attempted
to restore order to the fiscal system, with some success. From the end of
2021, as reports of a gathering humanitarian crisis grew, aid and cash flows
to the country improved. In February, the US Government announced that it
would seek to release about one-half of the reserves it had frozen. The Afghani
appreciated sharply. The question of whom, if unfrozen, that money would benefit,
the Taliban or the Afghan people, loomed large in negotiations to release
the funds. A devastating earthquake in late June 2022 added urgency to the
talks, which resumed in Doha, Qatar, at the end of the month.</P><P
>Despite such temporary relief, Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s economic outlook remains
bleak. The economy is expected to shrink significantly in 2022 and 2023; the
war in Europe arising from Russia&amp;rsquo;s invasion of Ukraine in February
2022 has exacerbated already high inflation, and the more than 500,000 additions
to the workforce annually will face a difficult job market. While the Taliban
rules most of the country, its military power can be challenged, especially
in view of cuts to defence spending. The risk of another insurgency is a real
one.</P><P
>The regime shift and the return of economic crisis raise questions about
the country&amp;rsquo;s long-term outlook. Beyond the immediate geopolitical shocks
and natural disasters, what are the development challenges for Afghanistan?
History helps us to answer that question. Western media discourse on the country
insists on the need to restore women&amp;rsquo;s freedom and democratic politics.
However, Afghanistan is no stranger to economic collapse and insurgency, and
these threats are more longstanding than the Taliban worldview. What, then,
makes economic development such an unstable process in this country?</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Conclusion</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P58"
>The violent history of Afghanistan
could suggest that the country is a failed state, but this is far from the
case. It is a divided state, and the root of this division lies in its history
and geography.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P59"
>For exactly a century, since a
state-directed economic modernization drive began in Afghanistan in 1920,
the economy of the country has been torn between two forces: centralization
and fragmentation. A development programme designed and directed from the
capital city could not reach far out to the countryside and the provinces.
Acute resource poverty and a tradition of regional autonomy that survived
because the centre was militarily weak or dependent on the local elite divided
Kabul from the regions and the two halves fell further apart as the modernization
project succeeded in the more prosperous areas. The insurgency and civil war
of the late 20th century were the most recent and perhaps the most violent
manifestations of the problem. This was a time in Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s economic
history when the centralization force was subdued, and fragmentation ruled.
The return of a stronger state, albeit with foreign military and technical
aid, changed the game, but no observer can say that it changed the game radically.
Economic development has returned, but it has accentuated inequality, and
it without significant foreign aid, no development path is feasible anyway.</P><P
>In short, with its poor soil, limited water resources, untapped mineral
resources and landlocked position, Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s economic base has always
been too weak to raise the taxes and finances necessary to form a government
that can both hold military power and spend significant amounts of money on
public goods. To become a viable nation state as well as an agent of development,
the country must rely on foreign money, coming in as aid, investment, remittances
or tradeable services (such as tourism). Historically, the periods of relative
prosperity and growth in the country were the periods when external economic
relations improved. With its negative image, the Taliban regime is an unlikely
candidate to draw in resources. Its predecessor, propped up with politically
compromised aid, was not a satisfactory alternative either.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P60"
>There are positive factors. Although
it is too early to say, global warming, by increasing the melting of snow
in the Pamir mountains, could potentially increase the flow of the crucial
Amu Darya river in northern Afghanistan. There are already signs that this
is happening. Although this raises the risks of flooding (and summer droughts),
the process presents the prospect of making more water available for agriculture
and urban use, if sufficient investment is made.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P61"
>Furthermore, whereas one factor
for the success of warring groups in the country was the falling cost of the
technology commonly used in small-scale warfare, one of the main factors for
the success of the centralizing development-focused state in recent years
has been improvements in the technology and institutions in the service of
health care and infrastructure. The former factor remains a challenge for
the modernization project and could lead to a permanent, if an unofficial,
division of the country. The latter factor holds much more positive promise.
The recovery stage over the past two decades involved the construction of
assets and institutions that could potentially survive with the will of the
new regime. The future depends on these assets and institutions.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.ECONOMY.SASIA.2022.P62"
>However, the joint effect of conflict
and the COVID-19 pandemic has reversed many of the solid gains made since
2002, as the country seems at risk of falling victim once again to the divisions
that have often blighted its economic and social progress.</P></GEN-SECTION></COUNTRY-SURVEY>
