<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?IS10744 arch
  name="SLlink to Oxygen"
  public-id="-//STEP//NOTATION SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  dtd-public-id="-//STEP//DTD SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  renamer-att="SLNames"
?><?ATTLINK table-block id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK table-block-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK chronology id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK res-institutes id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK political-profile-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK commodities id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnoteref slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK footnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK xr slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK anchor id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK intro-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group-content id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK is-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-table id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK directory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK article id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-overview id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK gen-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK essay id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK weights-and-measures id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK periodicals id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-table id "SLT"?><?Pub EntList AElig Aacute Abreve Acirc Agrave Amacr Aogon Aring Atilde Auml
 Cacute Ccaron Ccedil Ccirc Cdot Dagger Dstrok ETH Dcaron Eacute Ecaron Ecirc
 Egrave Emacr Eogon Euml Edot Gbreve Gcedil Gcirc Gdot Hcirc Iacute Icirc
 Idot Igrave Imacr Iogon Itilde Iuml Jcirc Lacute Lcaron Lstrok Nacute Ncaron
 Ntilde OElig Oacute Ocirc Ograve Omacr Oslash Otilde Ouml Racute Rcaron Sacute
 Scaron Scedil Scirc THORN Uacute Ubreve Ucirc Udblac Ugrave Umacr Uogon Uring
 Utilde Uuml Yacute Yuml Zacute Zcaron Zdot aacute abreve acirc aelig agrave
 amacr amp aogon aring atilde auml cacute ccaron ccedil ccirc cdot copy dagger
 deg dcaron dstrok eacute ecaron ecirc edot egrave emacr emsp ensp eogon eth
 euml euro frac12 frac13 frac14 frac34 frac23 gbreve gcirc gdot iacgr iacute
 icirc iexcl igrave imacr inodot itilde iuml lcaron ldquo lsquo lstrok mdash
 minus nacute nbsp ncaron ndash ntilde oacute ocirc odblac oelig ograve omacr
 oslash otilde ouml para racute rcaron rdquo rsquo sacute scaron scedil scirc
 sect tcedil thinsp thorn uacute ubreve?><COUNTRY-SURVEY
ORIGINAL-FILENAME="afggeog.rtf"
ID="AF.GE"
ISO="af"
ID-ROOT="af"
USAGE="sasia"
SECT-TYPE="GEOGRAPHY"
PRINT-STYLE="PGWIDTH"
><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="WestJ" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="maherj" fullname="Maher, Joanne"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="khanm" fullname="Meena Khan"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="matthewsc" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="obrienj" fullname="Jillian O'Brien"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="KhanMe"
fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="pshah" fullname="Priya Shah"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="pollardama" fullname="Pollard, Amanda"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="HigginsN" fullname="Higgins, Neil"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="shahp"
fullname="Priya Shah"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="sandhyac" fullname="C, Sandhya"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="KerrE" fullname="Elizabeth Kerr"?><COUNTRY-HEAD
>Afghanistan</COUNTRY-HEAD><HEADING
>Geography</HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="sasia"
TYPE="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE"
>Afghanistan</ALT-HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="sasia"
TYPE="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE"
>Geography</ALT-HEADING><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Physical Features</HEADING><P
>Occupying an area of 652,864&amp;nbsp;sq&amp;nbsp;km, Afghanistan is a landlocked
territory. To the north, it borders Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan and Tajikistan,
and, to the south and east, Pakistan. The latter frontier follows what was
once termed the Durand Line (after the representative of British India, Sir
Mortimer Durand, who negotiated it in 1893 with the ruler of Afghanistan).
There are borders to the west with Iran and to the north-east with the People&amp;rsquo;s
Republic of China. This last frontier was fully agreed only in 1963, and some
parts of the southern and western borders have still to be delimited.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.4"
>The main topographical feature of Afghanistan is a complex
of irregular highlands, which is relatively broad and low in the west and
very much higher and narrower towards the east. In this eastern part the mountains
form a group of well-defined chains, which are known by the general name of
the Hindu Kush (&amp;rsquor;Hindu destroyer&amp;rsquo;), and are linked further eastward
first to the Pamirs and then to the main Himalayan system. The Eastern Hindu
Kush ranges form the southern defining limit of the Wakhan strip while, a
short distance to the north and east, a small but high ridge, the Little Pamir,
forms the topographic link between the Hindu Kush and the main Pamir. From
maximum heights of 6,000&amp;nbsp;m&amp;ndash;7,000&amp;nbsp;m the peaks decline in altitude
westwards, attaining 4,500&amp;nbsp;m&amp;ndash;6,000&amp;nbsp;m in the zone close to
Kabul. Further west still, the ridges are no more than 3,500&amp;nbsp;m&amp;ndash;4,500&amp;nbsp;m
and in the extreme west they open out rather like the digits of a hand, with
much lower Parapamisus ridges (proto-Pamir) forming the last member of the
mountain complex. The various ridges are distinguished by separate names.
The Hindu Kush, which has a general altitude of about 4,500&amp;nbsp;m, with peaks
2,000&amp;nbsp;m&amp;ndash;3,000&amp;nbsp;m higher still, is, however, narrow and crossable
by quite a number of passes, some of which are indirect and snow-bound for
much of the year.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.5"
>Afghanistan forms a major watershed from which rivers flow
outward. The Amu Darya (Oxus) rises on the north side of the Hindu Kush and
flows north-westward into Turkmenistan. Here, away from the mountains, the
presence of small pockets of loess (a yellowish soil of high fertility) offers
scope for agriculture. The Hari Rud rises a short distance only from the Amu
Darya, but flows westward through Herat to terminate in a salt, closed basin
on the Iranian frontier. From the south and west of the Hindu Kush flow a
number of streams that become tributaries of the Indus; and in the extreme
south-west the Helmand river flows through arid country to end, like the Hari
Rud, in a closed basin that is partly within Iranian territory. The Helmand
basin is of interest in that, because of a curious balance in water-level
at its lowest part, the river here reverses its flow seasonally, and remains
for much of its length non-brackish instead of becoming progressively more
saline, as is normal when there is no outlet to the sea. The Helmand basin
thus offers distinct potential for agricultural improvement, including the
development of irrigation schemes; however, political difficulties (part of
the lower basin is Iranian territory) and remoteness have been inhibiting
factors.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.6"
>The lower-lying areas, which are in the main more densely
populated, occur either as a series of peripheral zones to the north and south,
or as a series of interior valleys and basins between the main mountain ridges
of the centre. Largest of these areas is the piedmont lying on the northern
flanks of the mountains and dropping northward in altitude to merge into the
steppe&amp;shy;lands of former Soviet Central Asia. This is Balkh (or Bactria),
a region of, in places, light yellowish, loessic soils. An interior situation,
shut off from the sea by mountains, means that rainfall is deficient and falls
mainly over the mountains. Streams fed partly by mountain snowmelt straggle
across the plain, to lose themselves in the sand, feed salt swamps or, in
a few cases, join others to form larger rivers such as the Hari Rud. Much
of Balkh thus consists of semi- or full desert with sheets of sand and gravel
in many places, and, nearer the mountains, an outwash of larger, coarser scree.
Given stable political conditions, this region with its areas of highly fertile
loess soils and moderate water supplies offers much scope for economic development.
Long inhabited by pastoral nomads, and disputed politically by various claimants
(Afghanistan, Iran and the former Union of Soviet Socialist Republics), this
northern zone was developed rapidly with irrigated cotton-growing as a main
element.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.7"
>In the east is the Kabul basin, which is a relatively flat
zone hemmed in closely by steep mountain ridges. Some distance away to the
north-west, and reachable through two major passes, is the narrower Vale of
Bamian, while south-east of Kabul lies another fertile lowland zone around
Jalalabad. Here lower elevation and southerly situation produce warmer conditions,
especially in winter, as compared with most of the rest of Afghanistan.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.8"
>In the south-east, extending through Ghazni as far as Qandahar,
there is another series of cultivated zones, but the extent of this piedmont
area is much smaller than the corresponding one described above as Balkh.
To the west, aridity, the price of declining altitude, increases, so the lowland
passes into the desert areas of Registan and the Dasht-i-Mayo. Registan has
seasonal flushes of grass, which support relatively large numbers of pastoral
nomads, who, however, are becoming increasingly settled following irrigation
development on the Helmand and Arghandab rivers.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Climate</HEADING><P
ID="AF.GEOG.10"
>Climatically, Afghanistan more closely resembles Iran and
the Middle East than it does south Asia, in that it has an almost arid summer,
a small amount of rainfall and considerable seasonal variation in temperature.
The monsoon&amp;shy;al condition of heavy summer rainfall experienced elsewhere
in south Asia does not occur. Annual rainfall ranges from 100&amp;nbsp;mm&amp;ndash;150&amp;nbsp;mm
in the drier, lower areas of the west and north, to 250&amp;nbsp;mm&amp;ndash;400&amp;nbsp;mm
in the east; on the highest mountains there is more still. Kabul, with an
average of 330&amp;nbsp;mm per annum, is typical of conditions in the east, and
Herat with 125&amp;nbsp;mm typical of the west. Almost all this falls in the period
December to April, though there can be a very occasional downpour at other
times, even in summer, when a rare damp monsoon&amp;shy;al current pen&amp;shy;etrates
from the Indian lowlands. Temperatures are best described as extreme. In July
the lowlands experience tempera&amp;shy;tures of 43&amp;deg;C, with 49&amp;deg;C not uncommon&amp;mdash;this
is true of Jalalabad on the edge of the Indus lowlands. Yet the effects of
altitude are important, and Kabul, at an elevation of 1,800&amp;nbsp;m, does not
often experience tempera&amp;shy;tures of over 38&amp;deg;C. Winter cold can be bitter,
with minima of &amp;minus;22&amp;deg;C to &amp;minus;26&amp;deg;C on the higher plateau areas,
and, as a result, there are heavy blizzards in many mountain areas. The Janu&amp;shy;ary
mean in Kabul is &amp;minus;4&amp;deg;C. A further difficulty is the preva&amp;shy;lence
of strong winds, especially in the west, where a persistent and regular wind
blows almost daily from June to September.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Population</HEADING><P
ID="AF.GEOG.11"
>The considerable variation in the types of terrain, and
the substantial obstacles imposed by high mountains and deserts, have resulted
in significant ethnic, linguistic and cultural diversity. The Pashtuns live
mainly in the centre, south and east of the country, and are probably numerically
the largest group. The Ghilzai, also of the areas adjacent to Pakistan, are
thought to be of Turkish origin, like the Uzbeks who live in the north, mainly
in the Amu Darya lowlands. Another important element comprises the Tajiks
and the Hazara, who speak Farsi. Most Afghans are Muslims of the Sunni sect.
The Hazara and the Qizilbash of Kabul are predominantly Shi&amp;lsquo;a. Pashto
(Pakhto), one of the eastern group of Iranian languages, is the main language
of the Pashtuns and is spoken by around 40%&amp;ndash;55% of the country&amp;rsquo;s
population, according to the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization (UNESCO). (A sizable community of Pashto speakers lives across
the border in Pakistan, numbering some 15% of the population of that country,
according to UNESCO). Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s other official (and most widely
spoken) language is Dari, a dialect of Farsi.</P><P
ID="AF.GEOG.12"
>Economic progress has been inhibited by a difficult topo&amp;shy;graphy,
an extreme climate with a generally deficient rainfall, and political instability.
Traditionally, small communities lived by cultiva&amp;shy;tion where water and
soil were available, and there were relatively numerous pastoralists, mostly
nomads, who formed an import&amp;shy;ant section of the community. Even today,
a significant proportion of the population is nomadic, and tribal organization
is st<?Pub Caret?>rong. In 2018, according to the Food and Agriculture Organization
of the United Nations, only 11.8% of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s total area was classified
as arable land.</P><P
>According to the census of June 1979, Afghanistan had a population of 13,051,358.
By 2021/22, according to official estimates, the settled population had increased
to 32,069,160, giving an average density of 49.1 per sq&amp;nbsp;km. (These estimates
excluded the nomadic population, broadly estimated at 1.5m. in 2011, and Afghan
refugees living outside of the country, of whom the Office of the United Nations
High Commissioner for Refugees estimated there were 2.1m. at May 2022.)
The capital, Kabul, is situated in the east of the country and had a population
of 4.4m. in March 2021, according to official estimates. The next largest
cities are Qandahar (with a population of 632,601, Herat (574,276) and Mazar-i-Sharif
(484,492).</P></GEN-SECTION></COUNTRY-SURVEY>
