<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?IS10744 arch
  name="SLlink--New"
  public-id="-//STEP//NOTATION SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  dtd-public-id="-//STEP//DTD SigmaLink link architecture//EN"
  renamer-att="SLNames"
?><?ATTLINK table-block id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK table-block-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK chronology id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK res-institutes id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK political-profile-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK commodities id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK endnoteref slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK footnote id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK p-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK xr slid "SLA"?><?ATTLINK anchor id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK intro-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-group-content id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK is-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK territory-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-table id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK ss-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK directory id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK dir-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK article id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK bibl-entry-expanded id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-overview id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK country-survey id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK gen-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK essay id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK weights-and-measures id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK periodicals id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-group id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-entry-simple id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK int-org-section id "SLT"?><?ATTLINK stats-table id "SLT"?><?Pub EntList AElig Aacute Abreve Acirc Agrave Amacr Aogon Aring Atilde Auml
 Cacute Ccaron Ccedil Ccirc Cdot Dagger Dstrok ETH Dcaron Eacute Ecaron Ecirc
 Egrave Emacr Eogon Euml Edot Gbreve Gcedil Gcirc Gdot Hcirc Iacute Icirc
 Idot Igrave Imacr Iogon Itilde Iuml Jcirc Lacute Lcaron Lstrok Nacute Ncaron
 Ntilde OElig Oacute Ocirc Ograve Omacr Oslash Otilde Ouml Racute Rcaron Sacute
 Scaron Scedil Scirc THORN Uacute Ubreve Ucirc Udblac Ugrave Umacr Uogon Uring
 Utilde Uuml Yacute Yuml Zacute Zcaron Zdot aacute abreve acirc aelig agrave
 amacr amp aogon aring atilde auml cacute ccaron ccedil ccirc cdot copy dagger
 deg dcaron dstrok eacute ecaron ecirc edot egrave emacr emsp ensp eogon eth
 euml euro frac12 frac13 frac14 frac34 frac23 gbreve gcirc gdot iacgr iacute
 icirc iexcl igrave imacr inodot itilde iuml lcaron ldquo lsquo lstrok mdash
 minus nacute nbsp ncaron ndash ntilde oacute ocirc odblac oelig ograve omacr
 oslash otilde ouml para racute rcaron rdquo rsquo sacute scaron scedil scirc
 sect tcedil thinsp thorn uacute ubreve?><COUNTRY-SURVEY
ORIGINAL-FILENAME="afghist.rtf"
ID="AF.HI"
ISO="af"
ID-ROOT="af"
USAGE="sasia"
SECT-TYPE="HISTORY"
PRINT-STYLE="PGWIDTH"
><?Pub Tag atict:info tracking="on" ref="0"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="LoveJ" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="DevrajV" fullname="Vani Devraj"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="matthewsc"
fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="KhanMe" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="MK" fullname="adm-SangheraH"?><?Pub Tag atict:user
user="sandhyac" fullname="C, Sandhya"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="User" fullname="cmarcham"?><?Pub Tag atict:user user="FrameI" fullname="FrameI"?><HEADING
>History</HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="sasia"
TYPE="SECTION-LONG-UPPERCASE"
>Afghanistan</ALT-HEADING><ALT-HEADING
USAGE="sasia"
TYPE="COUNTRY-SHORT-TITLECASE"
>History</ALT-HEADING><AUTHOR-GROUP
><PRIMARY-AUTHORS
><PERSON-NAME
><FORENAME
>Shubhangi</FORENAME><SURNAME
>Pandey</SURNAME><REGNAL
>Public Policy Analyst, The Economist Intelligence
Unit, New Delhi, India</REGNAL></PERSON-NAME></PRIMARY-AUTHORS><OTHER-AUTHORS
>Revised for this edition by <PERSON-NAME
><FORENAME
>Iftikhar H.</FORENAME><SURNAME
>Malik</SURNAME><REGNAL
>Professor Emeritus of History, Bath Spa University,
Bath, United Kingdom</REGNAL></PERSON-NAME></OTHER-AUTHORS></AUTHOR-GROUP><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Introduction</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P1"
>Afghanistan is located at the crossroads
of Central Asia and South Asia, with the Iranian plateau to its west. Linking
three distinct cultural and geographical regions, its location is often understood
as its greatest asset, as well as its bane. In the time of the ancient Silk
Road, with some of its major cities situated at the intersection of key regional
trading routes, Afghanistan benefited immensely from the mercantile exchange
that took place and remained a hub of regional trade and transit for a long
period. In contemporary times the country&amp;rsquo;s potential to facilitate
increased economic connectivity in the region is acknowledged by most regional
actors. More recently, its vast wealth of largely untapped minerals and natural
resources, estimated to be worth US&amp;nbsp;$1,000,000m.&amp;minus;$3,000,000m.,
has come into sharp focus.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P2"
>The same geography, however, has also
meant that Afghanistan has featured in various expansionist agendas by external
actors aiming to increase their geopolitical influence; it has often been
seen as a battleground of imperial, colonial and international conflicts.
From falling prey to invaders crossing over from Persia or Central Asia, including
Alexander the Great and Mahmud of Ghazni to name but two, to witnessing domination
by assertive imperialist forces such as the United Kingdom, with which Afghanistan
fought four wars between 1839 and 2021 before forcing it to retreat, Afghanistan
has witnessed more conflict than most other medium-sized countries. Following
the Partition of India in 1947, it was the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
(USSR) that wielded most relative influence over Afghanistan, directly as
well as indirectly, through pro-Moscow Afghan rulers. During the Cold War
era, Afghanistan was a theatre of contestation between the Great Powers of
the USSR and the USA, which eventually led to Soviet domination over Afghan
economic planning and policy formulation. None the less, the USA continued
to provide material support to local Afghan warlords who were opposed to the
Soviet-backed regime. It was this persistent struggle by two superpowers for
influence that became one of the defining characteristics of Afghanistan in
the latter decades of the 20th century.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P3"
>Another significant theme in the Afghan
sociopolitical milieu in the 1980s and the 1990s was internal strife along
ethnic and ideological lines for political control of the country. Even as
Afghans succeeded time and again in expelling foreign invaders by mounting
popular military mobilization, the country&amp;rsquo;s various militias and tribal
groups remained at loggerheads over the question of sharing power. The most
prominent manifestation of the internal power struggle was what followed the
Soviet invasion of Afghanistan in 1979, with some militias supporting the
communist regime and others fighting to resist and overthrow it. A similar
struggle continued even after the withdrawal of the USSR in the late 1980s
and created the ideal ground for the Taliban movement to emerge and establish
the &amp;lsquo;Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo; in 1996 with the help of
material patronage from some of its sympathetic neighbours. The Taliban, although
invoking the principles of Islam to justify their rule, further factionalized
Afghan society on ethnic lines. Being of Pashtun descent themselves, they
persecuted several non-Pashtun groups, declaring them to be enemies. Moreover,
the Taliban did not succeed in installing an effective, legitimate government
and were quickly defeated in the USA&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;war on terror&amp;rsquo; after
the Islamist militant group al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida (which the Taliban had harboured)
launched suicide attacks on US cities using civilian airliners in September
2001. Although the Afghan population initially welcomed the support of foreign
forces in driving the Taliban out of power, amid hopes for the country&amp;rsquo;s
reconstruction, questions around who would rule the country remained unresolved,
especially due to misgovernance and continuing violence.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P4"
>Emerging from the trend of perpetual
internal strife and conflict was the third defining characteristic of the
time, which was a crisis of political legitimacy resulting in a lack of institutional
stability. Following the Soviet invasion in 1979, although traditional domestic
adversaries formed short-term alliances to collectively fight the external
threat, regular patterns of fighting between rival Afghan groups resumed soon
after the foreign forces had been defeated in the late 1980s. There was no
centralizing authority in Afghanistan that could bind the ethnically diverse
society together and command political legitimacy.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P5"
>The restoration of a strong central government
proved particularly difficult after the final withdrawal of Soviet forces
in 1989, especially when compared with the broadly seamless installation of
central leadership after the civil war in 1929. By the early 1990s a significant
proportion of foreign aid had stopped reaching Afghanistan, as the erstwhile
active major powers were no longer interested in Afghan affairs, including
the orderly repatriation of refugees. Furthermore, the militarily emboldened
tribal groups, led by former <I
>mujahidin</I> (holy warriors), stood in strong
opposition to the political elite based in the capital, Kabul, which hindered
the latter from exercising unassailable authority. Even in the post-2001 reconstruction
following the fall of the Taliban, the relationship between the central Government
and local units of tribes and communities, which traditionally enjoyed considerable
autonomy in governance, remained unclear, if not totally conflicted. Instead
of first conditioning the Afghan people into accepting a new way of life,
the Government that was established after 2001 under Hamid Karzai set about
immediately implementing wide-ranging socioeconomic reforms concerning women,
modern education and individual rights&amp;mdash;themes that had traditionally
been staunchly contested by the largely conservative majority of Afghan society.
Not surprisingly therefore, popular disillusionment with the new Government
began to grow, which aided the resurgence of the Taliban. Night raids by US-led
forces, drone attacks and rising civilian casualties, alongside the concentration
of wealth and power among the warlords, disillusioned a vast majority of ordinary
Afghans.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P6"
>Taken together, these three overarching
themes have shaped the historical trajectory of Afghanistan since 1979 and
continue to characterize its dynamics today. Afghanistan continues to witness
low-intensity contestation among global powers, as well as the traditional
pronounced interest of major regional stakeholders. The controversial presidential
elections of 2019 and the subsequent feud that unfolded between political
rivals Mohammad Ashraf Ghani (the then incumbent President) and Dr Abdullah
Abdullah (the former Chief Executive of Afghanistan) robbed the unity government
of the considerable legitimacy that it would have otherwise enjoyed. The Taliban
began to publicize its intermittent victories against a factionalist regime
in Kabul, gradually consolidating power in outlying areas and declaring the
moral high ground over the Government, which it considered to be a puppet
of the USA. Having taken over Afghanistan by military means in 2021, the group
professes its commitment to ruling in peace. In order to best understand the
changing notions of power and political legitimacy and how they translated
into successive periods of instability in Afghanistan, it is necessary to
trace the evolution of political participation in the country. To that end,
the next section will explore the events that led to the Soviet invasion of
Afghanistan in 1979, including the Saur Revolution of 1978 and the subsequent
rise of disparate <I
>mujahidin</I> militias, who were variously aided and
abetted by the USA, Pakistan, Iran, the People&amp;rsquo;s Republic of China and
Saudi Arabia.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Daoud&amp;rsquo;s Republic and the Saur Revolution, 1973&amp;ndash;78</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P7"
>Afghanistan was proclaimed a republic
for the first time in its history in 1973. In a largely bloodless coup, Lt-Gen.
Sardar Mohammad Daoud Khan ousted his cousin, the ruling monarch King Mohammad
Zahir Shah, and the monarchy was abolished. Daoud declared himself President
of the newly formed republic, and his regime garnered support from various
sections of society and the institutional apparatus. Reaping the benefits
of the goodwill that he had cultivated in his previous tenure as Prime Minister
during 1953&amp;ndash;63, he was hailed by the military for facilitating the training
of young cadres in the USSR, and supported by the Pashtuns, who favoured his
idea of &amp;lsquo;Pashtunistan&amp;rsquo;, which aimed to wrest Pashtun territories
from Pakistan. His earlier efforts at making the Islamic face veil optional
for women in public, as well as other proposed social reforms, had also won
him the support of the relatively liberal sections of society, although monarchists
and some conservative Afghans felt resentful of his coup.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P8"
>Referencing the lack of economic progress
in preceding decades, Daoud embarked on an ambitious programme to facilitate
industrial growth, promote trade and revitalize domestic production. In 1977
he introduced a new Constitution, which sought to modernize the state, while
establishing a one-party presidential system with complete state ownership
of natural resources and fundamental industries. When Pakistan facilitated
Afghan Islamist uprisings against Daoud, owing to his support for Pashtun
separatists in the region, Daoud unleashed a wave of arrests and executions
of those who resisted him. As a result, many rebels escaped to Pakistan in
search of safe havens, among them Gulbuddin Hekmatyar of the Islamist Hizb-i-Islami
and Burhanuddin Rabbani of Jamiat-i-Islami. While Daoud continued to receive
Soviet patronage in the form of economic assistance, military training and
debt relief, he was keen on diversifying sources of foreign aid, which was
essential for him to realize his modernization plans for Afghanistan. He secured
a US&amp;nbsp;$2,000m. aid package from Iran and reached out to a number of other
regional countries for support, including Iraq and Saudi Arabia.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P9"
>However, Daoud&amp;rsquo;s tightening grip
over the Government and gradual sidelining of the Marxist People&amp;rsquo;s Democratic
Party of Afghanistan (PDPA), to which he had previously been close ideologically,
increased local opposition to his regime. Furthermore, his ties with the USSR
also began to weaken, owing to his suppression of prominent communist voices
and the presence of officials from the USA and the North Atlantic Treaty Organization
(NATO) in Afghanistan. Supposedly, it was persistent pressure from the USSR
that led to the unification of the two factions operating under the PDPA banner
at the time: the relatively moderate and socialist faction called Parcham
(Banner) and the radical Khalq (People) faction, which was in favour of overthrowing
the existing regime through violent means, invoking the communist instrument
of a &amp;lsquo;proletarian revolution&amp;rsquo;. In what came to be known as the
'Saur Revolution', the PDPA launched a coup on 27 April 1978 to overthrow
Daoud&amp;rsquo;s regime, in the process killing him and members of his family
at the presidential palace in Kabul. Amid the coup, the Revolutionary Council
of the Democratic Republic of Afghanistan was formed, and Nur Mohammad Taraki
of the Khalq faction in the PDPA was declared Prime Minister and Chairman
of the Council, while Babrak Karmal and Maj. Aslam Watanjar were designated
Deputy Prime Ministers. Seats in the Council were equally divided between
Khalq and Parcham members.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P10"
>However, the PDPA regime did not enjoy
as much popular support as it had hoped for, and resistance to the communist
way of governance began to grow. The socioeconomic policies of the Taraki
administration, although aimed at creating a more progressive and gender-equal
society, offended the sensibilities of the conservative rural population.
The initiation of mixed-sex education, limitations on the practice of dowry,
which in the Afghan context was the &amp;lsquo;price&amp;rsquo; that the groom paid
for the bride, as well as controversial land reforms that brought large land
holdings under state ownership, riled the local religious and tribal communities,
turning them against the Government. Moreover, dissent between the Khalq and
Parcham factions contributed to the rapid destabilization of the regime, with
Hafizullah Amin (a co-founding member of the PDPA) eventually ousting Taraki
and ordering his assassination in September 1979. He declared himself President
and General Secretary of the PDPA. The apparent fragility of the regime prompted
the Soviets to invade Afghanistan on 24 December to stabilize the communist
cause in the country and prevent any other overarching ideology from taking
root.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Soviet Decade, 1979&amp;ndash;89</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P11"
>Despite their awareness of the emerging
cracks in PDPA ranks, the Soviets were not quick to advocate direct intervention
in Afghanistan. Even in May 1978, many in the Soviet Politburo, including
Yurii Andropov, the head of the Soviet Committee for State Security (KGB),
were explicitly against the idea of invasion, arguing that the socioeconomic
milieu of Afghanistan was not yet conducive for pure socialism, and that acting
via their &amp;lsquo;bayonets&amp;rsquo; instead to stabilize the situation would
be more prudent. However, the ousting of Taraki and successive efforts by
Amin to reach out to Pakistan and more importantly the USA spurred a re-evaluation
of the approach in Moscow. By late October 1979 the Committee on Afghanistan
in the Soviet Politburo had ratified the recommendation of invasion, and in
a matter of weeks the Soviet leader Leonid Brezhnev officially ordered the
intervention. With careful planning and discreet execution, which entailed
the disruption of communication lines in Kabul and other major cities, the
seizure of radio stations and the encirclement of Amin&amp;rsquo;s palace, Darul
Aman, the Soviets had installed about 50,000 of their troops in Afghanistan
by 27 December. The Soviets, wary of Amin&amp;rsquo;s intentions and expecting
defections among Afghans, ordered his assassination and replaced him with
the more moderate Karmal.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P12"
>Even as the Soviets placed boots on
the ground in Afghanistan, the USA initially abstained from responding militarily
to the communist takeover. It was only with the kidnapping and eventual killing
of the US ambassador to Afghanistan, Adolph Dubs, in February 1979, at the
hands of leftist rebels, that the USA altered its engagement strategy vis-&amp;agrave;-vis
Afghanistan. While the USA had advised the Afghan Government to not attempt
a rescue mission for Dubs, fearing that he would become collateral damage
in combat between the two sides, the Government sent in troops anyway, and
US fears were vindicated. As a result, the USA revoked all aid to the Afghan
Government, suspecting Soviet involvement in the Dubs incident, and launched
&amp;lsquo;Operation Cyclone&amp;rsquo; to arm the anti-establishment <I
>mujahidin</I> fighters, many of whom were also being trained in Pakistan for rebellion.
Both the USA and the USSR were, of course, fighting battles of their own all
the while, under the pretext of bringing stability to Afghanistan. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P13"
>While the Soviets had intended to leave
Afghanistan as soon as the communist regime was strengthened sufficiently,
local resistance to the prolonged presence of &amp;lsquo;foreign elements&amp;rsquo;
grew remarkably fast and acquired profoundly nationalistic tones. By promulgating
the opposition as fighting a <I
>jihad</I> (holy war) against &amp;lsquo;infidel
invaders&amp;rsquo;, the mobilized masses or the <I
>mujahidin</I> overcame internal
factionalism and presented a united front in the name of Afghanistan and Islam.
The <I
>mujahidin</I> had also joined hands with Islamist parties led by the
likes of Rabbani and Hekmatyar, who had been operating out of Pakistan since
escaping the wrath of Daoud in the mid-1970s. The Pakistani-based groups were
deemed essential in the fight against Soviet intervention, as they brought
with them a ready supply of foreign aid and arms, particularly from the USA
and Saudi Arabia. China also agreed to provide a variety of combat equipment
to the rebels at the behest of the USA, although it equally served its purpose
of frustrating a longstanding foe, the USSR.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P14"
>After coming to power, Karmal attempted
a number of outreach efforts to appeal not only to the communists, but the
non-communist Afghans as well. From announcing prisoner releases, especially
those detained at the infamous Pul-e-Charkhi prison on the outskirts of Kabul,
to revoking the contentious land reforms, encouraging the return of Afghan
refugees from neighbouring countries and installing non-PDPA individuals in
the Government, Karmal tried everything to win back popular support. By then,
however, most Afghans had resolved to join anti-Soviet forces, and the PDPA
Government was largely considered a Soviet puppet. Although Karmal had proclaimed
the establishment of a unity government, out of the 28 ministers in his cabinet,
only three were from a non-PDPA background. The formation of the National
Fatherland Front to co-opt opposition groups, as well as exemptions in the
implementation of land reforms, also failed to create a broader support base
for the Soviet-backed Government.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P15"
>Acknowledging that the PDPA Government
lacked popular support and the resources required to administer control, the
USSR decided to take recourse in their tested strategy of re-educating the
youth. The modified school curriculum included espionage training for children
under the Young Pioneers Programme and membership of the Democratic Youth
Organization, where young people were taught the skills of surveillance and
propaganda. The Afghan intelligence agency supervised the political and ideological
conditioning of children and young adults in training centres. By encouraging
the teaching of a relatively passive version of Islam in <I
>madrassas</I>,
Karmal and the Soviet authorities also attempted to cultivate a subservient
class of the clergy, given that the existing clerics were themselves a factionalized
community and therefore beyond the possibility of getting co-opted. Public
sentiment against the regime strengthened, however, and manifested in the
&amp;lsquo;Allah-u-Akbar&amp;rsquo; or the &amp;lsquo;3 Hut&amp;rsquo; uprising in February
1980.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P16"
>Meanwhile, factionalism within PDPA
ranks continued to grow, often turning violent as in the case of the party
congress that took place in March 1982, where infighting claimed the lives
of five party members. Even after Karmal expanded the party membership to
include a substantial number of Khalqis, the clash of ideologies between the
two major PDPA factions continued. The PDPA's armed wing was also reconstituted
to reflect Khalq predominance, which the regime hoped would reconcile the
radical faction with the mainstream Parchamis. However, the move backfired,
as Khalqi officers began to openly flout the directives of Karmal and often
refused to fight the local <I
>mujahidin</I> groups. Supported by Pakistani-based
militant groups, the <I
>mujahidin</I> became increasingly sophisticated in
their use of weapons and offensive strategies. To further strengthen the <I
>mujahidin</I> against Soviet forces, US President Ronald Reagan authorized
aid worth US&amp;nbsp;$3,200m. for the rebels, which was routed via Pakistan in
the guise of military and economic support. With the arrival of Stinger anti-aircraft
missiles provided by the USA in 1986, which could be used to shoot down low-flying
Soviet helicopters, the balance of power shifted significantly in favour of
the <I
>mujahidin</I>, leaving the Soviets worried about the future of the
socialist revolution in Afghanistan.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P17"
>The intervention took its toll on the
Soviets as well. Even though they had almost 111,000 troops in Afghanistan
at the peak of the deployment, who were able to prevent the Afghan resistance
from overthrowing the communist administration, the financial cost of the
war was more than the USSR could accept, not least afford. By the mid-1980s
the maintenance of combat forces in Afghanistan was costing the USSR about
2,000m.&amp;ndash;3,000m. roubles a year, with casualty figures reaching unanticipated highs. Moscow had begun to
face intense diplomatic backlash and international condemnation for its invasion
of Afghanistan and for the conflict-induced displacement of millions of war-weary
Afghans to the neighbouring countries of Pakistan and Iran. In the decade
of Soviet occupation from 1979 to 1989 almost 6m. Afghans had reportedly fled
the country across the porous borders in search of refuge, accounting for
the displacement of almost two-fifths of the total Afghan population. Simultaneously,
within the USSR domestic support for the invasion had begun to wane. However,
it was only after the death of Brezhnev in 1982 and two of his successors
in short order (Andropov in 1984 and Konstantin Chernenko in 1985) that Mikhail
Gorbachev assumed charge of the Communist Party of the Soviet Union, marking
a significant shift in the Soviet strategy in Afghanistan. He declared negotiation
as the most desirable means of ending the war, instead of continued combat,
and sought to strengthen the PDPA government internally, as part of his long-term
exit strategy for the USSR.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P18"
>On the political front, despite his
efforts at co-opting the non-communists into the regime and encouraging the
creation of Government-affiliated, quasi-independent organizations to represent
diverse voices at key decision-making forums, Karmal was despised by the majority
of Afghans for being a Soviet stooge. As a result, when Gorbachev came to
power in the USSR, Karmal was replaced as the General Secretary of the PDPA
by Dr Najibullah Ahmadzai, the erstwhile chief of the Afghan intelligence
agency, who was a Pashtun but also a devoted Parchami. After an initial power
struggle between Najibullah and Karmal, who was still the leader of the ruling
Revolutionary Council, the Soviets eventually exiled Karmal to Moscow and
declared Najibullah as the head of the Democratic Republic of Afghanistan
in November 1986. Thereafter, Najibullah rapidly consolidated power and began
the ideological move away from socialism to nationalism. In 1987 he convened
a Loya Jirga (a Grand National Council of local leaders), at which a new Constitution
was drafted, multi-party democracy was established, and Najibullah was declared
as the President of the republic. The elections held in May 1988 accorded
electoral legitimacy to the decision of the Loya Jirga in the previous year.
He renamed the PDPA as the Hizb-i-Watan (Homeland Party) and accommodated
local resistance groups within a coalition Government, in return for harmony.
One such offer was made to Ahmad Shah Masoud of the anti-Soviet Jamiat-i-Islami
political party, albeit unsuccessfully. The hardliners within the PDPA expressed
disappointment with the shift away from the revolutionary reform agenda previously
followed by Taraki and Amin, but Najibullah attributed this to the continued
Soviet presence, not his own policies, and believed that local dynamics would
change drastically upon eventual Soviet withdrawal.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P19"
>Once Najibullah came to power and the
Republic of Afghanistan began to resemble the republic under Daoud in the
1970s, Gorbachev turned to the United Nations (UN) to facilitate negotiations
between the warring parties, which would allow the Soviets to eventually retreat
from Afghanistan. By announcing the withdrawal of 8,000 troops in July 1986,
Gorbachev intended to signal to all stakeholders in the Afghan war that he
was serious about finding a political solution to the conflict. The USA, however,
remained sceptical about the move, citing reports that some 6,000 KGB personnel
and special commandos had arrived in Afghanistan to replace the withdrawn
troops. None the less, Gorbachev announced in February 1988 that all Soviet
troops would leave the country in about a year, which accelerated the ongoing
UN-brokered talks. Soon enough, the Governments of Afghanistan and Pakistan
signed three agreements, collectively known as the Geneva Accords, in the
presence of the USA and the USSR as guarantors. The Accords, besides establishing
a relationship based on the principle of non-interference, declared Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s
right to self-determination and the right of Afghan refugees to return home
peacefully, and set the date for the withdrawal of Soviet troops. The UN Good
Office Mission in Afghanistan and Pakistan, which was created by the UN Secretary-General
Javier P&amp;eacute;rez de Cu&amp;eacute;llar soon after the agreements were signed,
monitored the phased withdrawal of Soviet troops, which was completed on 15
February 1989, as mandated by the Accords. Henceforth it was the responsibility
of the elected Afghan Government and the local warlords to decide the future
of their homeland.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Rise and Fall of Najibullah</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P20"
>Following the departure of the Soviets,
the shared <I
>mujahidin</I> cause of fighting the infidel enemy by means of
waging <I
>&amp;lsquo;jihad&amp;rsquo;</I> had ceased to have justification, as the
fight was now among fellow Muslims within Afghanistan. However, as the USA
and the USSR continued to provide covert military aid to their respective
benefactors (namely, the <I
>mujahidin</I> and the Afghan Government), despite
this being in violation of the UN-brokered withdrawal agreement, insurgent
attacks on the Government rose sharply. As a result, the strategy of co-opting
dissenters into the establishment to dampen the resistance also became increasingly
ineffective, given that the Government was visibly overpowered by the sheer
numbers of the rebels. To capitalize on the rising <I
>mujahidin</I> forces,
Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s Inter-Services Intelligence mobilized the Peshawar-based
Afghan resistance parties, popularly known as the &amp;lsquo;Peshawar 7&amp;rsquo;,
into forming the Afghan 'government in exile' in February 1989 in an attempt
to seize Jalalabad and declare a new regime. However, in the absence of an
integrated command structure and experience in fighting an army with conventional
military means, the mobilized <I
>mujahidin</I> failed embarrassingly at the
hands of the PDPA.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P21"
>After the d&amp;eacute;b&amp;acirc;cle of Jalalabad,
the number of insurgents willing to reach a peaceful bargain with President
Najibullah grew considerably. Najibullah incorporated many of them into leadership
roles within his Government, while also allowing them a significant degree
of autonomy to operate their independent militias. Abdul Rashid Dostum, an
Afghan of Uzbek origin, was one such prominent local leader who ran his own
Government-supported militia of some 20,000 multi-ethnic fighters, who often
fought the <I
>mujahidin</I> alongside government forces. The declining numbers
of active <I
>mujahidin</I>&amp;mdash;from about 85,000 in 1989 to some 55,000
in 1990&amp;mdash;demonstrated the effectiveness of Najibullah&amp;rsquo;s strategy.
In fact, the Government-affiliated militias had now begun to outnumber the
resistance forces, as well as the Government-controlled troops. The troops
had themselves become fragmented, primarily inspired by the ever-evolving
alliances between the <I
>mujahidin</I> and the political establishment. The
steady supply of economic aid from the USSR, on top of the covert military
assistance mentioned above, helped Najibullah to foster increased support
for his regime by investing in networks of patronage and building up military
strength.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P22"
>Najibullah was aware of the importance
of seamless transit of Soviet aid for the stability and continuation of his
Government. Unsurprisingly therefore, it was the northern militias, such as
in the provinces of Balkh and Baghlan, which the Government brought under
its influence and associated most closely with, owing to their geographical
proximity to the USSR. The provinces in the east and the south, however, were
not as cohesive as the north and were in any case dominated by the Peshawar-based <I
>mujahidin</I> parties and prone to their pervasive infighting. Although the
formation of the National Commanders Shura by a group of influential Afghan-based <I
>mujahidin</I> was perceived as a potential threat by Najibullah, the adoption
of gradual and relatively moderate tactics by the body proved to be inadequate.
Differences with their counterparts patronized by Iran equally hindered the
formation of a cohesive platform to oust Najibullah.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P23"
>By August 1991, with the USSR weakened
by internal political instability and unable to keep up its commitment of
supplying food and fuel to the Afghan Government, Najibullah&amp;rsquo;s hold
over the country began to diminish. In the absence of adequate funds to pay
off the militias in return for loyalty in service, many chose to align with
the anti-establishment <I
>mujahidin</I> instead, which themselves were not
a homogenous group. Also notable was the increasing level of corruption in
the Najibullah Government, where the practice of civil servants filling their
own coffers with incoming Soviet aid, instead of redirecting it to the public,
had become rampant. A financially crippled and militarily drained Najibullah
was finally compelled to reach out to the UN to facilitate a political transition
and in the process bring some semblance of peace and stability to Afghanistan.
Rattled by the idea of a political reorganization taking place, the disparate <I
>mujahidin</I> groups had begun to consolidate alliances of their own, with
the aim of ousting the existing regime in Kabul. Fearing the fast-increasing
levels of insurgent violence, Najibullah agreed to step down as President
in early 1992 and, unable to flee the country, he took cover in the UN compound
in Kabul. (In the end, however, Najibullah's fate was sealed when the Taliban
stormed the UN facility in Kabul on 27 September 1996, mercilessly killing
him and then parading his castrated body around the city to signal the beginning
of a new era&amp;mdash;of the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan.)</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Challenge of Assimilation and <I
>Mujahidin</I> Rule, 1992&amp;ndash;96</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P24"
>With the successful removal of Najibullah
from power and the dismantling of the PDPA-regime that he had left behind,
the <I
>mujahidin</I> had proved their tenacity. With a power vacuum at the
centre, three prominent <I
>mujahidin</I> leaders in Afghanistan&amp;mdash;Masoud,
Dostum and Kayani&amp;mdash;rallied their respective Tajik, Uzbek and Ismaili
militias into one cohesive force and prepared to establish a base in Kabul.
The other leading contender in the fight for political supremacy was Hekmatyar,
joined by the radical Khalqis of the PDPA. However, it was Masoud&amp;rsquo;s
coalition that emerged victorious in capturing Kabul and successfully warding
off a takeover by Hekmatyar. Instead of dictating the constituents of the
new transitional Government himself upon arrival in Kabul, Masoud thought
it better to defer the task to the Pakistani-based parties, in order to avoid
conflict on ethnic lines and possibly also to offer an olive branch to his
staunch rival, Hekmatyar.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P25"
>The Pakistani-based <I
>mujahidin</I> parties,
functioning as the Islamic Jihad Council (the advisory body for the newly
formed Afghan Government), had been eyeing control of Afghanistan themselves.
Given their lack of physical involvement in the war and the popular support
that Masoud enjoyed, however, they had to settle for the power-sharing agreement
brokered by Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif on 24 April 1992,
formally known as the Peshawar Accord. The agreement established a Transitional
Council, with Prof. Sibghatullah Mojaddedi of the National Islamic Salvation
Front as the head, and Rabbani set to take over from him after two months.
Masoud was appointed as the Minister of Defence in the transitional Government,
but Hekmatyar refused to accept the prime ministerial position that had been
offered to him.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P26"
>However, the apparent cohesiveness among
the various elements of the transitional government did not last long, and
the country fell deeper into chaos and despair. Atrocities committed upon
the Afghan population increased, and lawlessness prevailed. Opium cultivation
became the mainstay of the country&amp;rsquo;s economy, the profits from which
were used generously to fund local criminal networks. Smaller militias and
warlords, with their shifting allegiances, who were elevated to prominence
during Najibullah&amp;rsquo;s reign, now became important actors in determining
power dynamics at the national level. Some of the most formidable <I
>mujahidin</I> militias in Afghanistan included the Ismailis in the north-east of the
country led by the Naderis, Shi&amp;rsquo;a Hazaras from central Afghanistan,
the Achakzai Pashtuns in Qandahar and the Herat-based militia led by Ismail
Khan, who later aligned with the Jamiat-i-Islami leaders in Kabul. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P27"
>Alliances between <I
>mujahidin</I> groups
were formed based on evolving personal rapports among the leaders, rather
than based on ideological convergences, making defection from one group to
another a regular practice. This was most frequently demonstrated by Dostum,
who switched over to Hekmatyar&amp;rsquo;s side in January 1994, betraying his
former allies, although their joint offensive proved ineffective in the face
of a strengthened government force. Abdul Ali Mazari&amp;rsquo;s Hizb-i-Wahdat,
mainly a Hazara resistance group, was also a part of the unsuccessful alliance
with Hekmatyar. On the whole, however, there was a lack of agreement among
the various warring factions about the form and membership of a future government.
Furthermore, although most of the factions were capable of defending their
respective regional strongholds, none was equipped sufficiently to dominate
the others and declare themselves victorious. While Herat and the western
provinces of Badghis, Farah and Ghor were held by Ismail Khan, the alliance
of Dostum and Mazari&amp;rsquo;s Hizb-i-Wahdat ruled in the north. Masoud controlled
Kabul and the north-east of the country. As for the smaller regional commanders,
at no point did any of them claim complete independence, extending their support
to either the Rabbani-Masoud grouping or to Hekmatyar. Although Rabbani remained
the President of the Islamic State of Afghanistan from 1992 until 1994, his
writ was limited to the areas directly under the control of his commanders,
which in practice did not extend far beyond the palace in which he was residing.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P28"
>For the four years that Afghanistan
was ruled by the <I
>mujahidin</I>, the country plummeted deep into anarchy,
as a ruthless civil war gripped the nation. To put an end to protracted violence
in Afghanistan, the UN Special Mission in Afghanistan attempted to facilitate
a process of political reconciliation between the warring <I
>mujahidin</I> in
March 1994. However, even though the various Afghan factions had agreed to
the formation of a well-represented central authority to oversee the settlement
process, the initiative came to an abrupt halt in late 1994, with the Taliban
takeover of the city of Qandahar.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Emergence of the Taliban Movement, 1994&amp;ndash;96</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P29"
>The origins of the Taliban movement
can be traced back to the <I
>madrassas</I> (religious schools) in Pakistan
in the 1980s, aided by the military regime of President Mohammad Zia-ul-Haq. <I
>Talib</I> (Taliban being the plural) means &amp;lsquo;student&amp;rsquo; or &amp;lsquo;seeker
of religious knowledge&amp;rsquo;. The <I
>madrassas</I> were the only source of
education to the millions of Afghan refugees who had escaped to Pakistan following
the Soviet invasion of Afghanistan. Many such <I
>madrassas </I>were operated
by the Jamiat-e-Ulema-e-Islami (JUI) party of Pakistan, which as an institution
was deeply opposed to a reformation or broadening of religious ideals and
beliefs. That the <I
>madrassas</I> provided free food and lodging to the students
made the idea of them even more appealing to the refugees who were struggling
to survive displacement and poverty. Most of the Taliban fighters in the early
1990s were students recruited from such <I
>madrassas </I>located in the Pashtun
areas of Pakistan. In that regard, the Taliban movement was remarkably different
from the leadership of the other Afghan <I
>mujahidin</I> groups or parties,
many of which comprised educated Muslims who had been involved in the political
evolution of Afghanistan at various points in time.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P30"
>Given the poor, mostly rural background
of most of the movement&amp;rsquo;s constituency, the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s meteoric
rise in the mid-1990s was astounding to many. However, at least three key
factors can be identified. The first and possibly the most crucial factor
was ideological and material patronage that the movement received from Pakistan.
Not only did the Taliban leadership have close links with the religious parties
in Pakistan (such as the JUI), but they also received arms and cash from them,
which proved instrumental in helping the militant group to seize Qandahar
in November 1994. The second important factor was factionalism among the existing
Afghan <I
>mujahidin</I>: no faction was able to command political legitimacy
or to establish predominance militarily, or even willing to negotiate a compromise.
The third key component of the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s rise was the ability of the
movement&amp;rsquo;s leadership to give its followers a goal worth fighting for.
The earlier interpretation of <I
>jihad</I> waged by the <I
>mujahidin</I> in
the 1980s, premised on the idea of fighting an &amp;lsquo;infidel enemy&amp;rsquo;
to protect Islam, had become redundant. Therefore, the Taliban, capitalizing
on the power struggle among the Afghan <I
>mujahidin</I> factions, indoctrinated
their own followers with the idea of a &amp;lsquo;new&amp;rsquo; <I
>jihad</I> that
would put an end to the lawlessness that prevailed in Afghanistan at the time,
as well as the suffering of the common people. Having lived a life of extreme
hardship as refugees, the recruited youth bought into the Taliban ideology
and became desperate to defeat the <I
>mujahidin</I> outlaws and reclaim their
place in the homeland. The largely tribal population of Afghanistan had also
become disillusioned by the self-interested <I
>mujahidin</I> groups in the
country and looked to the Taliban as a far better alternative. The profusion
of regional warlords, often engaged in internecine warfare and turpitude,
brought willing cadres to the Taliban from across the predominantly Pashtun
regions in the country. Little did Afghans realize that the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s
initial campaign to restore law and order would be followed by the imposition
of radical Islamist policies derived from a strict interpretation of <I
>Shari&amp;lsquo;a</I> (Islamic law).</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P31"
>Before capturing the city of Qandahar
in November 1994, the Taliban, led by their founder and chief Mullah Omar,
had attacked Hekmatyar&amp;rsquo;s weapons depot located at the border crossing
of Spin Boldak, with operational support from the Pakistani military. Reportedly,
they seized over 18,000 AK-47 rifles and other arms from the strategic post.
Thereafter, the Taliban proceeded to Qandahar, where they are reported to
have offered a large sum of money to the local commander, who then handed
over control of the city to them without a fight. Such operational victories
helped the Taliban to amass a considerable amount of weaponry, which added
to their military strength, which was also being built up by generous material
support from Pakistan. For its part, Pakistan arguably thought of the Taliban
as its vehicle to acquire strategic depth within Afghanistan and a stable
economic route to newly opened Central Asia. Within a few months of acquiring
Qandahar, the Taliban had established control over about a dozen provinces
in the southern part of the country, which was predominantly Pashtun, much
like the Taliban's membership. Only after the movement had established a firm
grip over a sizeable chunk of the country did it venture towards Kabul. Although
Masoud and his fighters succeeded in pushing back the Taliban from the capital,
and Ismail Khan foiled their attempts at capturing Herat, the Taliban wasted
no time in gearing up for renewed, deadlier attacks in the future.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P32"
>After Dostum defected to the Taliban
in mid-1995 and brought with him a significant number of Uzbek <I
>mujahidin</I> fighters who still pledged loyalty to him, the Taliban gained an competitive
edge. Furthermore, strengthened by the generous military assistance provided
by Pakistan, Saudi Arabia and Osama bin Laden (a Saudi-born millionaire and
the spiritual leader of al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida), who reportedly donated US&amp;nbsp;$3m.
to the group, the Taliban became a force to be reckoned with. With the capture
of the city of Jalalabad in September 1996, the Taliban had wiped out Hekmatyar&amp;rsquo;s
stronghold in the east of the country, using the same tactics as in Qandahar:
challenging the local factionalist commanders in exchange for surrender. Now
adept at making political and strategic appeals to win over adversarial forces
and the laity&amp;mdash;very often without any resistance from the opposite side&amp;mdash;the
Taliban advanced towards Kabul. In anticipation of the approaching danger,
Masoud abandoned Kabul to return to the Panjshir Valley in the north-east,
leaving Kabul for the Taliban to take over. It is important to note, however,
that Masoud did not crumble under pressure from the Taliban and instead went
on to establish the anti-Taliban Northern Alliance, together with Rabbani,
in late 1996. Switching sides yet again, Dostum too joined the Alliance, after
the Taliban had captured Kabul. </P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan: The Taliban Years, 1996&amp;ndash;2001</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P33"
>Soon after the Taliban captured Kabul,
Mullah Omar convened a <I
>shura</I> (council) comprising 1,200 members of
the <I
>ulema</I> (religious scholar community), who declared him as the <I
>Amir-ul-Momineen</I> (Commander of the Faithful). In October 1997 Omar officially
renamed the country as the Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan and took office
as the head of state, although he was based in Qandahar. Rejecting the traditional
Afghan system of governing through Loya Jirgas, Omar instead established two
governing councils: the Inner Shura, which he led personally, and the Central
Shura, which reported to Omar and was intended to manage civic administration
and foreign relations. However, such an arrangement proved to be ineffective
in administering the entire population in the long term and eventually gave
way to an improved structure of administration in 1999. In the revised format,
the Qandahar-based Inner Shura was retained as it was, but the Central Shura
was dissolved in favour of separate ministries for each area of administration.
Even so, the change proved merely symbolic as the Qandahar Shura continued
to have the final say in all matters, and the ministers often found their
decisions being dismissed or overturned.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P34"
>By September 1996 the Taliban controlled
some 70% of the entire Afghan territory, except the north, which was Masoud&amp;rsquo;s
stronghold. To eliminate the looming threat of being attacked by the remaining <I
>mujahidin</I> strongmen, the Taliban thought it best to go on the offensive
and further consolidate their territorial reach. With the help of a defecting
commander, the Taliban succeeding in forcing Bagram out of Masoud&amp;rsquo;s
shadow. In the case of the city of Mazar-i-Sharif, a defecting local commander,
Abdul Malik, facilitated the takeover by the Taliban. However, owing to a
power struggle that ensued between Malik and the Taliban after the former&amp;rsquo;s
defection, Malik switched back over, which forced the group to retreat from
Mazar-i-Sharif after a number of its fighters were killed. In response to
the humiliation suffered in Mazar-i-Sharif, the Taliban imposed a food blockade
on the predominantly Hazara (an ethnic minority) population of the city, which
threatened to drive them into mass starvation. In August 1998 the Taliban
once again attempted to capture Mazar-i-Sharif, and this time they succeeded
in the endeavour, unleashing a massacre on the Hazaras.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P35"
>When the Taliban came to power, they
were initially commended for the security that they provided, especially in
regions that had only witnessed bloodshed, political rivalry, chaos and absolute
lawlessness during the <I
>mujahidin</I> years. Soon enough, however, the Taliban's
radical religious and social policies based on <I
>Shari&amp;lsquo;a</I>, and often
inspired by the <I
>pashtunwali</I> (the tribal code of the Pashtuns), began
to alienate the non-Pashtun population. Religious and ethnic minorities such
as the Hazaras and other Shi&amp;rsquo;a communities were regularly persecuted.
Opium cultivation and related trade underscored the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s activities,
some of the profits from which were reportedly distributed among criminal
networks. Taliban policies towards the female population were particularly
severe, given that they banned women from engaging in employment outside of
their homes and eliminated the two key sectors that women were most integral
to: education and health care. Some of the offences that warranted corporal
punishment&amp;mdash;in some cases taking the form of public executions in stadiums&amp;mdash;were
homosexuality and adultery. Men who failed to keep long beards in keeping
with the Taliban directive were gaoled and all forms of entertainment were
banned. Symbols of modernity and socioeconomic progress were vehemently condemned
by the Taliban, as they associated modern values with imperialist forces like
those of the British and the Russians, which had invaded Afghanistan at different
points in time. Ancient archaeological structures and artefacts were not spared
either; notably the Taliban destroyed the ancient Buddha statues at Bamian
in February 2001, in the name of protecting Afghans from falling prey to idolatry.
Similarly to contemporary Saudi Arabia, the Taliban established the Ministry
for the Propagation of Virtue and Suppression of Vice, which was to ensure
compliance with the strict laws of the group and inflict severe punishments
on those who failed to obey.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P36"
>While the Taliban regime had come to
be widely criticized by certain sections of the population in Afghanistan,
internationally it was also unable to secure diplomatic recognition and hence
faced isolation by most countries. In fact, apart from Pakistan, Saudi Arabia
and the United Arab Emirates (UAE), no other country ever officially recognized
the Taliban as the legitimate ruling authority of Afghanistan, although some
nations, and a few international corporations, dealt with them indirectly.
Allegedly, the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s military assistance to Central Asian rebels
and Islamist fighters from the Xinjiang region of China, by way of providing
moral support and training, had destabilized large parts of the region and
further alienated Iran, the Russian Federation and China. In particular, the
Islamic Movement of Uzbekistan&amp;mdash;a violent, anti-Government force&amp;mdash;had
also been allowed to set up a base in northern Afghanistan, which spurred
radicalization in the Central Asian republic. The Taliban&amp;rsquo;s extensive
involvement with radical elements from foreign countries indirectly inspired
disaffected Muslim youths, including converts to the religion, all around
the world to take up <I
>jihad</I> in the name of an Islamic revolution.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P37"
>The global isolation of the Taliban
was underscored by Omar&amp;rsquo;s increasing proximity to bin Laden, the leader
of al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida. After orchestrating attacks against US troops in Saudi
Arabia and Somalia, bin Laden had been expelled from Sudan in May 1996, which
led him to seek refuge in Afghanistan. By establishing solid ties with the
Taliban, as a result of taking Omar&amp;rsquo;s daughter as one of his wives,
bin Laden was able to set up an al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida base in the country. This
association bestowed a significant amount of prestige and moral validation
upon bin Laden in the eyes of fellow Islamist fighters across the globe, since
Omar commanded respect as the <I
>Amir-ul-Momineen</I> of the Islamic world.
During the Taliban's reign of Afghanistan, it is estimated that al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
was able to train no less than 11,000 fighters in the country, several of
whom were involved in the terrorist attacks on the USA in September 2001.
In return, al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida offered the Taliban assistance in terms of training,
a ready supply of radicalized fighters and other services, including the assassination
of key Afghan figures who opposed Taliban rule. The relationship between the
two Islamist groups was therefore one of mutual benefit.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P38"
>However, the Taliban's relationship
with al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida soon started becoming problematic. After al-Qa`ida bombed
US embassies in Kenya and Tanzania in August 1998, claiming many lives in
the process, the Administration of the US President Bill Clinton unleashed
targeted cruise missile attacks on al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida&amp;rsquo;s strategic bases
in Khost, Afghanistan. Saudi Arabia also reacted strongly against the Taliban,
when the latter refused to extradite bin Laden upon a Saudi request to do
so. India also felt aggrieved by the Taliban, when the group assisted al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
in negotiating the release of jihadist fighters from Indian prisons, in exchange
for the release of civilian passengers on board an Indian Airlines flight
that al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida hijacked in September 1999. Owing to the self-inflicted
threat of increased radicalization emanating from the <I
>madrassas</I> operating
in Afghanistan, the Pakistani Government also felt hesitant about continuing
its proximity with the Taliban. Several years of economic stagnation, coupled
with US sanctions imposed in response to nuclear tests undertaken by the country
in 1998, only added to Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s reluctance in sustaining the lines
of credit to the Taliban&amp;mdash;a provision that had been partly responsible
for the group&amp;rsquo;s rise to supremacy in the first place. Operationally,
however, the decisive blow to the Taliban came after al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida terrorists
successfully executed attacks on the World Trade Center in New York and the
Department of Defence (&amp;lsquo;the Pentagon&amp;rsquo;) in Washington, DC, in September
2001 after hijacking civilian airliners, killing almost 3,000 civilians. It
was the last straw for the USA, which had thus far refrained from deploying
troops on the ground to fight the terrorists in Afghanistan, but was now prepared
to launch a concerted global &amp;lsquo;war on terror&amp;rsquo; against some of those
Afghans who had been its allies against the former Soviet Union during the
1980s.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P39"
>The USA&amp;rsquo;s counter-terrorism campaign,
code-named &amp;lsquo;Operation Enduring Freedom&amp;rsquo;, garnered the support
of most of the countries that felt threatened by the Islamist forces in Afghanistan.
Pakistan too, under President Pervez Musharraf, pledged support for the US
effort, wanting to distance Pakistan from the Taliban, which was now the object
of international contempt. After the Taliban refused two significant US requests&amp;mdash;to
hand over the mastermind of the terrorist attacks against the USA and to prevent
Afghanistan from being used as a sanctuary for Islamist terrorists&amp;mdash;the
USA was left with no option but to enter the battlefield itself. US aircraft
began to bombard Taliban and al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida positions in Afghanistan from
early October 2001, while US special forces were deployed on the ground and
persuaded anti-Taliban tribal militias to fight alongside them. In November
some 3,000 troops drawn from NATO member states joined the USA&amp;rsquo;s war
effort. The USA began to provide financial and military assistance to the
anti-Taliban Northern Alliance, which also received material support from
Russia. A militarily bolstered Northern Alliance succeeded in seizing Herat,
Mazar-i-Sharif, Jalalabad and even Kabul from the Taliban, forcing it to retreat
south. With the signing of the Bonn Agreement in Germany in December, Taliban
rule over the country officially came to an end, and Omar surrendered his
remaining fighters to local commanders, eventually making his own escape to
Pakistan. Most of al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida&amp;rsquo;s cadres and resources had been eliminated
by the coalition forces. As for the political future of Afghanistan, the Agreement
authorized the setting up of a six-month interim government that would oversee
the functioning of the country until domestic conditions were conducive for
elections to be held. Hamid Karzai was appointed as the Interim President
of the Afghan Transitional Administration.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Karzai Years: Challenges of Reconstruction and Insurgency, 2001&amp;ndash;14</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P40"
>In the absence of functioning government
machinery, the establishment of the Transitional Administration agreed upon
at the Bonn Conference was an important reconstruction imperative for the
USA and its allies. The Kabul-based interim Government, with Karzai as its
head, received recognition from most quarters internationally. Almost six
months after the Transitional Arrangement was appointed, a Loya Jirga was
convened in Kabul in June 2002, where Karzai was elected as the President
of the interim Government almost unopposed, as the two other contenders, former
King Zahir Shah and Rabbani, had rescinded their candidatures. The Loya Jirga
was ethnically and regionally well represented, with some 1,450 delegates
drawn from all the existing administrative divisions, and Karzai received
a warm welcome by the public at large. To emphasize the inclusivity of the
new interim administration, Karzai promptly appointed a 35-member Constitutional
Commission, which included six women. The draft Constitution presented by
the Commission was ratified by another Loya Jirga in January 2004, which in
effect gave birth to the Islamic Republic of Afghanistan, where freedom of
religion was guaranteed and the pronounced official role of the clergy became
minimal. Together with a strong presidency, the Constitution also provided
for a bicameral National Assembly, comprising the upper house (Meshrano Jirga),
and the lower house (Wolesi Jirga), which was to be elected by the people.
Upholding the Afghan tradition of locally organized administrative units,
the Constitution also mandated the election of provincial, urban and local
councils. Presidential elections were successfully conducted with help from
the UN on 9 October 2004, with some 25,000 polling stations for people to
cast their vote in Afghanistan, as well as in the Afghan refugee camps in
Pakistan and Iran. Winning by a clear margin, Karzai was officially elected
as the President on 7 December, beginning his first term amid great enthusiasm.</P><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Internal Weaknesses</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P41"
>Although the formation of the new Government
was a respite from the political chaos and drama that Afghanistan had witnessed
over the previous three decades, Karzai proved unable to consolidate power.
Instead of building a centralized government, Karzai appointed familiar regional
warlords in key portfolios, including senior positions in the military, presumably
in the hope of co-opting them. For instance, Masoud&amp;rsquo;s successor Mohammad
Qasim Fahim was appointed as the defence minister, while Dostum, who had become
infamous for his shifting allegiances, was awarded a senior commanding position
within the military. Resources were also distributed based on personal relationships
rather than merit or a legitimate mandate. Charges of rampant corruption and
maladministration had begun to be levelled against Karzai&amp;rsquo;s model of
administration. Given the weak central structure, the Government could not
ensure physical and economic security much beyond Kabul, especially in the
rural parts of the country, which constituted the majority of the territory
and population. The Government&amp;rsquo;s heavy reliance on international donors
to fund even the most rudimentary infrastructure projects such as schools
and hospitals further diminished the establishment&amp;rsquo;s political legitimacy
in the eyes of ordinary Afghans. Moreover, as the financial backers of the
projects, international partners dictated development priorities rather than
the Government, which resulted in a stark disconnect between the results achieved
and Afghans' aspirations. The post-2001 political reorganization therefore
highlighted an inherent contradiction at play in Afghan society: although
devolved political power was not able to bring security and economic progress
to the people, heavily centralized authority could also not have served the
purpose, as regional autonomy and political participation were widely desired
ideals. In addition, the US-led military campaigns across the country, including
night raids, deportations, and internments at Bagram Air Base and Guant&amp;aacute;namo
Bay, in Cuba, engendered serious questions about the legitimacy and efficacy
of the Karzai administration. Karzai often found himself torn between ethnic
loyalties, national imperatives and Western prerogatives, exacerbating ill
will on all sides.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P42"
>While the Afghan Government&amp;rsquo;s
economic and strategic dependence on foreign actors arguably detracted from
the regime&amp;rsquo;s legitimacy and authority to govern, most Afghans no longer
resisted an international military presence in the country. Foreign powers
were, in fact, thought of as a bulwark against the depredations of local warlords.
An important expectation from the foreign forces in Afghanistan was that of
providing security to the people. In the immediate period after defeating
the Taliban, however, international troops were few in number and were largely
deployed in the southern and eastern parts of the country, to eliminate the
residual presence of the Taliban and al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida. The USA had explicitly
proclaimed a &amp;lsquo;light footprint&amp;rsquo; strategy for its military presence
in Afghanistan, as the majority of its forces needed to be deployed in Iraq
(after the USA had invaded and occupied that country in 2003). Meanwhile,
the role of the NATO-mandated International Security Assistance Force (ISAF)
was limited to protecting Kabul. It was only with the approaching Afghan presidential
elections in 2004 that the USA and NATO reinforced their deployments in Afghanistan.
In terms of financial aid, although Afghanistan was promised some US&amp;nbsp;$10,000m.
in aid for the initial years of reconstruction and another $14,000m. for the
2005&amp;ndash;11 period, many pledges never materialized, and most aid was distributed
by circumventing official government channels. Furthermore, infrastructure
projects failed to meet the expectations of job creation, as most of the initiatives
were completed unilaterally by foreign actors, without the involvement of
Afghans. The deployment of provincial reconstruction teams by the international
coalition forces in 2003, which were meant to ensure security while promoting
provincial administration and development, also proved to be inadequate in
achieving their fundamental objective.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P43"
>By 2005, soon after the successful execution
of the presidential elections, the USA was preparing for a reduced military
presence in Afghanistan. With the knowledge that it had achieved the decimation
of Taliban and al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida forces in the country, the USA considered that
it had accomplished its mission. However, the situation on the ground in Afghanistan
did not warrant such a drawdown of foreign troops. Insecurity was rising,
given the unchallenged domination of regional warlords and the inability of
Karzai's Government to control the rebels or instil confidence in the people.
The Government, facing serious corruption charges, had been unable to deliver
even basic amenities such as electricity, potable water and public transportation
to the people, let alone security. Against this background, Taliban forces,
which had been growing in numbers and strength in Pakistan after being expelled
from Qandahar in 2001, found the perfect opportunity to re-emerge in Afghanistan,
in an even deadlier shape than before. With the threat of resurgent Taliban
violence looming, US and NATO forces were compelled to increase their military
footprint in the country.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Taliban Resurgence</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P44"
>After initially being routed from their
strategic bases in southern Afghanistan in 2001, the majority of the leaders
of the Taliban and al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida had taken up residence in Pakistan, specifically
in the Federally Administered Tribal Areas or the North-West Frontier Province,
both of which are predominantly Pashtun regions. The two bodies had begun
to regroup as early as 2003, although clear manifestations of their resurgence
were only visible by 2004&amp;ndash;05, as attempts were made by the Taliban,
albeit unsuccessfully, to disrupt the presidential and parliamentary elections
held during that time. It is no surprise therefore that when the Taliban returned
to Afghanistan, it first sought a foothold in the primarily Pashtun provinces
such as Qandahar, Helmand, Zabul, Paktia and Paktika, all of which are predominantly
Pashtun and border Pakistan. Unlike in the 1990s, the Taliban now adopted
more sophisticated tactics to assert themselves militarily, making suicide
attacks and improvised explosive device blasts the &amp;lsquo;new normal&amp;rsquo;
in Afghanistan, inspired by the Iraq insurgency. In 2006 there was reportedly
an increase of some 200% in insurgent violence across the country, compared
with the previous year. It was also reported that the Taliban was working
in loose co-ordination with other insurgent groups in the country, collectively
mounting attacks on the Afghan Government and coalition forces. Other than
the Taliban, major insurgent groups included Hekmatyar&amp;rsquo;s Hizb-i-Islami
and the Haqqani network, led by Jalaluddin Haqqani, which were reputedly engaged
in narcotics trafficking to fund their respective activities. Al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
cadres were also reported to be fighting alongside the Taliban from 2009 onwards,
although operations by NATO special forces had greatly diminished the former
group&amp;rsquo;s outreach and following.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P45"
>Further exacerbating the security situation
was the deliberate strategy of the Taliban to attack international aid workers
and non-governmental organization (NGO) staff working on social and economic
rehabilitation programmes in Afghanistan. Although the practice of attacking
foreign humanitarian aid workers was evident even in 2003, by 2005 the Taliban
had made it an integral component of its insurgency, issuing a <I
>fatwa</I> (religious
pronouncement) to destroy all symbols and people associated with foreign occupation
in Afghanistan, even if non-violent. As a result, most international aid organizations
began to reduce their presence in the southern and eastern parts of the country,
where the Taliban were most influential, which were also the areas that required
the most rebuilding and assistance and were primarily inhabited by Pashtuns.
Taking advantage of these developments, the Taliban endeavoured to shift Pashtun
public opinion in favour of their idea of <I
>jihad</I> and created an overarching
narrative that portrayed foreign forces not only as enemies of Afghanistan
and Muslims, but also of Pashtuns in particular. The US-led invasion of Iraq
and the decimation of its infrastructure, followed by the Sunni&amp;ndash;Shi&amp;rsquo;a
conflict, further supported the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s attempts to persuade Afghans
of their commitment to Islam. By 2005, riding on the wave of minor victories
in the southern provinces, the Taliban had begun to establish their own &amp;lsquo;shadow
governments&amp;rsquo; and courts at district and provincial levels, in the areas
that they had gradually come to control.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P46"
>Taliban violence, often described by
them as resistance against non-Muslims in a Muslim country, escalated throughout
the first decade of the 21st century. The deterioration of the security situation
was attributed to the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s focus on attacking hitherto stable neighbourhoods
and cities and the use of sophisticated tactics and weapons by the insurgents,
which resulted in an increase in civilian deaths. Despite a number of international
conferences and conventions held during the period, such as the 2008 Paris
Conference in Support of Afghanistan, which launched the Afghanistan National
Development Strategy and pledged US&amp;nbsp;$21,400m. on behalf of the international
community, insurgent violence overshadowed all aspects of governance and development.
An increased presence of the UN Assistance Mission in Afghanistan, which was
agreed upon at an international conference on Afghanistan held at The Hague,
Netherlands, in March 2009, did not succeed in achieving peace or advancing
the reconstruction agenda in the country either.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P47"
>Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s descent into a reinvigorated
insurgency was due not only to remnants of the Taliban and al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
festering in the region, but more importantly driven by a severe lack of central
control over the countryside, the grossly inadequate military reach of the
foreign forces and the inability of the Government in Kabul to deliver economic
development and reform, in keeping with the expectations of the people. The
population in the Pashtun provinces had been particularly disillusioned with
Karzai&amp;rsquo;s Government for not protecting them from the depredations of
local insurgents and warlords, even after the fall of the Taliban. Furthermore,
defining their campaign as one of &amp;lsquo;counter-terrorism&amp;rsquo; rather than
&amp;lsquo;counter-insurgency&amp;rsquo;, the US special forces in Afghanistan were
apparently inflicting more damage on local infrastructure and institutions
than the reconstruction efforts could offset.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>International Stakeholders and Shifting Priorities</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P48"
>Under newly elected President Barack
Obama, the US Administration marked a significant shift in its Afghanistan
policy in early 2009. Among other developments, the USA now became a vocal
critic of the institutional and functional weaknesses of the Karzai Government
and realized that insecurity in Afghanistan was closely linked to patronage
networks in Pakistan. In keeping with the stated commitment of promoting democracy
in Afghanistan, the USA refrained from replacing Karzai with an appointment
of its own and instead supported the organization of a presidential election
in August 2009. However, the poll was undermined by countless complaints of
fraudulent practices such as proxy voting, underage voting and other irregularities,
which were reported to the Independent Election Commission (IEC) and the Electoral
Complaints Commission, leading to a recount of votes in the following month.
Arriving at the conclusion that neither of the two presidential contenders&amp;mdash;Karzai
and Abdullah Abdullah, a key Jamiat-i-Islami leader&amp;mdash;had secured over
50% of the votes, a second round of voting was announced. As Dr Abdullah had
made his participation in the second round of voting conditional upon certain
demands vis-&amp;agrave;-vis the constitution of the IEC, he chose to rescind
his candidacy when the demands were not fulfilled. On 2 November 2009 the
IEC announced that Karzai had been re-elected as President. However, Karzai&amp;rsquo;s
image as a weak and corrupt political leader in the eyes of the Afghan people,
as well as the international community, remained unchanged.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P49"
>Regardless of the outcome of the disputed
presidential elections, the Obama Administration continued to prioritize Afghanistan
in its new foreign policy agenda and adopted a new military strategy with
greater dependence upon drone aircraft to eliminate Taliban cadres and supply
lines. Responding to reports of increasing levels of insurgent violence, in
February 2009 President Obama ordered the deployment of another 17,000 US
troops to Afghanistan. The increased military presence was intended to oversee
the smooth execution of presidential elections and reinvigorate the US counter-insurgency
campaign in the country. By December 2009 another 30,000 US troops were sent
to Afghanistan, bringing the total number up to about 100,000. Another key
decision regarded the expansion of the Afghan army and police. From the target
of installing 80,000 troops in the army, the number was now fixed at 134,000
troops, with a projected expenditure of US&amp;nbsp;$10,000m. until 2014. Furthermore,
the new US strategy for Afghanistan also reflected the widespread concerns
about rampant corruption in the Karzai administration. However, the USA also
feared that any drastic reformation of the government machinery would cause
it to fall apart, leading to an even more disillusioned electorate. A noteworthy
break from the past was exemplified in the revised US strategy of dealing
with the Taliban, which now focused on empowering local leaders and possibly
arming small militias against the Taliban, even as the proposal sparked fears
of a new civil war erupting in the country. The year 2009 was declared as
the most violent year in Afghanistan since the fall of the Taliban in 2001.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P50"
>The International Conference on Afghanistan
held in London, UK, in January 2010 marked an important milestone for the
evolving political and security situation in Afghanistan. In keeping with
pledges made during President Karzai&amp;rsquo;s first public speech after securing
a second presidential term in 2009, the Conference laid the foundation for
foreign forces to gradually withdraw from the country, leaving Afghanistan
to be governed by its own people. Moreover, the Conference sought to provide
a framework for reconciliation with those insurgents who were willing to renounce
violence and accept the Government as a legitimate authority. The Consultative
Peace Jirga convened by President Karzai in June 2010 was held as a result
of a consensus arrived at in London, which was further reaffirmed by the international
community at the Kabul Conference in July. The Consultative Peace Jirga also
launched the Afghanistan Peace and Reintegration Programme, which aimed to
create a socioeconomic environment conducive to conflict transformation and
the integration of deradicalized belligerents into the mainstream. Another
significant step that built on the reconciliation agenda of President Karzai
was the formation of the High Peace Council to promote peace and national
unity throughout the country. Members of the Council regularly travelled to
countries in the neighbourhood and beyond, in order to cultivate support for
an Afghan-led peace process.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P51"
>As mandated by the London conference
and reaffirmed in successive meetings with the Afghan Government, President
Obama announced that the additional US forces that had been deployed in 2009
would be withdrawn by 2014, cutting the US military presence in the country
by about one-third. Stating that the primary objective of the US mission in
Afghanistan had been largely achieved, and that the latter no longer posed
a threat to US security, he affirmed that the withdrawal would continue in
a steady manner until security operations were handed over to Afghan forces
by the end of 2014. The US-Afghanistan Strategic Partnership Agreement, signed
by President Obama and President Karzai on 1 May 2012, provided for the possibility
of a continued, albeit limited, US presence in Afghanistan for a period of
10 years after the withdrawal of combat forces in 2014, essentially to train
Afghan forces and to target the remaining militants running the insurgency.
Although the Agreement did not specify the number of US troops to be maintained
in Afghanistan, it committed the Governments of the USA and Afghanistan to
negotiate the renewal of the Bilateral Security Agreement (BSA), in order
to decide the exact means of engagement. Similarly, at a NATO summit in Lisbon,
Portugal, in November 2010, representatives of the bloc had agreed to implement
a phased transfer of security responsibility to the Afghan Government by 2014,
with the latter gearing up to assume full control of and responsibility for
the national security and development agenda. In the meantime, NATO undertook
the responsibility of training the Afghan police and armed forces to enable
them to shoulder security responsibility around the country, but the Taliban
also increased its efforts to influence trainees with its own discretionary
propaganda.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P52"
>The emerging consensus on the withdrawal
of foreign forces notwithstanding, the security situation in Afghanistan continued
to deteriorate. Together with an increase in the frequency of assassinations
and lethal indiscriminate bomb attacks, the human cost of the war had also
come to include grave violations committed against civilians in the wake of
multiple aerial attacks with drones. There were also reports of children being
lured into carrying explosives unknowingly and thereby committing suicide
attacks on behalf of Islamist insurgents. Another key development on the security
front was the assassination of the head of the High Peace Council (and former
President) Rabbani in September 2011, by a suicide bomber posing as a Taliban
envoy. Rabbani&amp;rsquo;s assassination certainly undermined the tentative spirit
of reconciliation nationwide. A second Bonn Conference, held in December,
none the less succeeded in resurrecting the peace agenda and also included
proposals about the Taliban opening a diplomatic office to conduct formal
negotiations with the Afghan Government.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P53"
>The Taliban officially opened their
first representative office in Doha, Qatar in June 2013, but the event prompted
consternation on the part of the Karzai Government, as the signage outside
the premises, which had attracted much international media attention upon
its inauguration, was the office of the &amp;lsquo;Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;;
in addition, the flag of the Taliban flew over the building. Another point
of contention was a press release issued by the Taliban soon after the opening
of the Doha office, stating that it would engage in building diplomatic ties
with other countries before negotiating a settlement with the Afghan Government.
As a result, Karzai postponed the scheduled talks with the insurgent group,
describing the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s move as an attempt to establish a government-in-exile,
while according peripheral importance to the Afghan Government. This led to
the Taliban closing down the office temporarily. Karzai also suspended the
high-level negotiations on renewing the BSA with the USA, citing concerns
that the USA had not delivered on the promise of promoting Afghan-led peace
talks and had not achieved substantial progress in economic reconstruction
and overall security. Karzai&amp;rsquo;s refusal to sign the agreement that sought
to provide an expanded bilateral security framework not only strained US-Afghan
ties under the Obama Administration, but also aggravated security concerns
within Afghanistan. Western Governments seemed to have lost patience with
Karzai amid growing violence, a profusion of white-collar corruption and pervasive
war fatigue.</P></GEN-SECTION></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The National Unity Government of Ashraf Ghani and the Return of the
Taliban, 2014&amp;ndash;</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P54"
>Even as uncertainty continued to characterize
most spheres of governance and life in Afghanistan, and insurgent violence
continued unabated, presidential elections were held as planned, on 5 April
2014. Despite dire warnings&amp;mdash;primarily from the Taliban and Hizb-i-Islami&amp;mdash;threatening
Afghans with dire consequences if they voted in the polls, the turnout exceeded
expectations. Once again, as neither of the two leading candidates, Dr Abdullah
and Ghani, secured more than 50% of the votes, a second round of voting took
place on 14 June. As soon as the IEC announced that about 7m. voters had participated
in the election, Dr Abdullah contested the result, claiming massive electoral
fraud, and demanded an audit of the votes cast. As the audited results were
still unacceptable to Dr Abdullah, a more comprehensive audit of polling stations
was conducted by the IEC, supported by the UN and supervised by both contenders&amp;rsquo;
camps. Dr Abdullah and Ghani engaged in a dialogue to outline a political
framework for the soon-to-be established government, in which both agreed
to form a unity government and supported the creation of the position of Chief
Executive of the Government&amp;mdash;a position not recognized by the Constitution,
but with the understanding that the Constitution would be revised and a post
of Prime Minister established. On 21 September 2014, amid protests in Qandahar
against the formation of a unity government, Ghani was declared President
in the first peaceful transfer of power among elected representatives in Afghan
history in a popularly contested poll, while Dr Abdullah was appointed as
Chief Executive.</P><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>President Ghani&amp;rsquo;s Reform Agenda</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P55"
>As soon as President Ghani assumed office,
he proclaimed a robust agenda of multi-sectoral reform as the first order
of business. His initial efforts included a streamlining of the administrative
machinery and working towards improved co-ordination among official agencies
to target widespread corruption&amp;mdash;an enduring legacy of the previous regime.
Although a few experienced figures were appointed to key portfolios, President
Ghani ensured that no former or serving ministers were included in the new
cabinet. Ghani attempted to make up for a delay in cabinet appointments by
charging the ministers with the formulation of policies that they intended
to implement in the first 100 days in office, which were thereafter pronounced
publicly to build popular confidence in the political leadership, so that
they could be held accountable for their actions, or lack thereof. Instilling
the idea of mutual accountability between the provincial councils and municipal
authorities was also made an indispensable objective. The reform agenda extended
to the judiciary and included a comprehensive review of the credentials of
existing staff and the establishment of a special court to review the cases
of political officials who had been charged with corruption and financial
fraud. Ghani also reopened an embezzlement case relating to the privately
owned Kabul Bank in 2010, in which some US&amp;nbsp;$1,000m. worth of foreign
aid went missing, and organized for a public trial to be held for the suspected
perpetrators of the fraud. Such measures instilled a cautious optimism among
people in urban Afghanistan, along with greater receptivity in the Western
regimes, yet rural and tribal Afghans continued to hold scepticism, given
that the Taliban continued to administer some regions as a type of parallel
administration. The Taliban&amp;rsquo;s survival and even return despite a decade-long
campaign to the contrary began to find more listening ears in rural areas,
where economic underdevelopment and anger at drone strikes tempered any optimism
about the Ghani-Abdullah regime.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P56"
>Although Afghanistan was traditionally
a subsistence economy, President Ghani strongly believed that in future, the
country&amp;rsquo;s economic progress would be closely tied to regional trade
and transit co-operation. So, while he sought to overhaul the public finance
management system domestically, he also committed Afghanistan to important
transcontinental connectivity ventures such as the Turkmenistan&amp;ndash;Afghanistan&amp;ndash;Pakistan&amp;ndash;India
gas pipeline project and the Five Nations Railway Corridor (crossing China,
Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Afghanistan and Iran), calling the &amp;lsquo;cluster
approach to infrastructure&amp;rsquo; the future of co-operation. President Ghani,
together with Chief Executive Dr Abdullah, leveraged the Regional Economic
Cooperation Conference on Afghanistan, which had been initiated in Kabul in
2005 and convened frequently thereafter, as a platform to rally regional support
for a collective approach to economic growth, investment and development in
Afghanistan. The formation of the National Procurement Board allowed the Government
to make payments judiciously for the implementation of public projects aimed
at domestic infrastructure development, unlike the previously arbitrary way
of allocating resources.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P57"
>Given widespread discontent with electoral
malpractice and fraud surrounding most polling, electoral reform constituted
another key component of President Ghani&amp;rsquo;s political mandate. The Government
began this process by establishing a Special Commission on Electoral Reform
in 2015, which was responsible for making recommendations to the President
on potential reforms for the electoral system and dispute settlement mechanisms,
as well as the management of electoral bodies. To further strengthen the integrity
of government institutions in the eyes of the public, Ghani ordered the creation
of a new IEC and an independent Electoral Complaints Commission. Some of the
other important electoral reforms implemented by Ghani included the establishment
of polling centres throughout the country to promote voter accessibility and
the use of biometric voter verification machines. Even though progress on
electoral reform was often marked by slow decision-making and hampered by
insurgent attacks on polling facilities, Ghani&amp;rsquo;s genuine commitment
to reforming the electoral system was encouraging.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>External Military Assistance and Domestic Chasms</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P58"
>Ghani&amp;rsquo;s election as President
marked a striking shift in the way that Afghanistan portrayed itself to the
outside world, particularly on the matter of receiving development and security
assistance. Whereas Karzai had been widely associated with entrenched corruption,
erratic decision-making and unreliable governance, Ghani came across to the
international community as much wiser and more pragmatic. An important manifestation
of international confidence in Ghani as a responsible recipient of aid was
the signing of the New Development Partnership Agreement with the USA in March
2015, wherein the USA pledged aid worth US&amp;nbsp;$800m. to promote sustainable
economic reform in Afghanistan. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P59"
>On security too, shortly after taking
office, in September 2014 President Ghani signed the BSA agreement with the
USA and a &amp;lsquo;status of forces&amp;rsquo; agreement with NATO in December,
in effect giving assent to a continued international military presence and
foreign assistance after most US troops had departed in 2014. As a result,
the complete withdrawal of ISAF troops and the end of NATO&amp;rsquo;s combat
mission in Afghanistan, which was completed on 31 December 2014 in accordance
with the 'status of forces agreement', was followed by the arrival of the
NATO-led Resolute Support Mission on 1 January 2015, with a limited mandate
to train, advise and assist the Afghan Government and the Afghan forces in
their counter-insurgency efforts. However, the process of withdrawal of US
forces was more complicated. Although President Obama had committed to bring
the number of US troops down to 9,800 by the beginning of 2015, which was
to be halved by the end of that year, the decision was reversed later in the
year, after Obama cited a longer military presence (until the end of 2017)
as vital for both US and Afghan security, even though the USA&amp;rsquo;s combat
mission in Afghanistan was over.</P><P
>Ghani&amp;rsquo;s dependence on Western security forces and external imperatives
would often hinder his own initiatives, which aimed to achieve greater national
consensus and regional co-operation; the USA and the EU often prioritized
the elimination of the Taliban opposition, placing the Ghani regime in a precarious
situation. His Government, like that of Karzai, was confronted with this balancing
act, and early optimism soon gave way to a growing disillusionment. Hasty
retribution after sporadic attacks by Afghan trainees against their Western
mentors and supervisors only helped the Taliban to portray the latter as enemies
of Islam and Afghanistan. The Taliban&amp;rsquo;s armed campaigns, while it concurrently
operated a diplomatic office in Doha, boosted its profile and gradually demoralized
the pro-Ghani elements in Kabul, Herat, Kunduz and elsewhere. It appeared
as if the Qandahar Shura and the Taliban leadership in Quetta and Qatar held
the de facto power as they challenged the remit and authority of the Kabul
regime.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P60"
>However, conflict continued unabated
throughout 2017 and well into 2018 and 2019, and attacks actually increased
in frequency and intensity. In line with the strategy devised for their spring
offensive, Operation Mansouri, which began in April 2017, the Taliban maintained
its stronghold of the southern provinces, while making a strategic advance
to the north. Dismissing government efforts to engage in direct talks in 2018,
the Taliban increasingly targeted urban areas and district administrative
centres. As a result, the Government deployed Afghan National Security and
Defence Forces (ANSDF) to the north of the country, which led to a dramatic
increase in clashes with the Taliban, damaging strategic lines of communication
and other vital infrastructure. While taking stock of the worsening security
situation, particularly rising civilian casualties, NATO announced an increase
in troops for its Resolute Support Mission to extend until the end of 2020.
The newly elected US President Donald Trump made a similar announcement in
August 2017, indicating a change in the strategy of military engagement, which
entailed increased air operations in co-ordination with the ANSDF. Furthermore,
the US Secretary of Defence James Mattis announced the deployment of an additional
3,000 troops in September, taking the total tally of US forces in Afghanistan
to 14,000. However, Trump had indicated during election speeches that he was
not interested in continuing with active US involvement in Afghanistan, making
Ghani&amp;rsquo;s position even more vulnerable.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>Reconciliation Efforts</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P61"
>Another significant characteristic of
the Ghani Government was its resolve to bring the Taliban to the negotiating
table as a necessary step to put an end to the apparently interminable conflict.
To that end, government representatives and members of the Taliban had met
in an informal meeting in Doha, organized by an international NGO, in May
2015. Although the meeting was unofficial, an important outcome was consensus
on the reopening of the political representative office of the Taliban in
Doha, to serve as the venue for peace talks in the future. To keep the momentum
going, President Ghani also stepped up diplomatic efforts to promote Afghan
peace and reconciliation with various regional stakeholders, particularly
Pakistan, given its historically close ties with the Taliban leadership. Stating
that Pakistan and Afghanistan faced &amp;lsquo;common enemies&amp;rsquo;, Pakistan
Prime Minister Nawaz Sharif hosted the first official peace talks between
the Afghan Government and the Taliban in the Pakistani capital, Islamabad,
in July 2015, in the presence of US and Chinese observers.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P62"
>The initial optimism around the official
start of negotiations, however, was short-lived as the Afghan Government&amp;rsquo;s
announcement in July 2015 of the death of Taliban chief Mullah Omar (he had
apparently died of tuberculosis in Kabul in April 2013) had created a rift
within the Taliban leadership over choosing Omar&amp;rsquo;s successor. Although
Omar&amp;rsquo;s long-time aide Mullah Mohammad Akhtar Mansour was appointed as
the new leader of the group at the end of July 2015, some members of the Taliban
opposed his leadership. Indicating a lack of internal consensus on making
peace with the Afghan Government, Mullah Mansour refused to countenance the
resumption of peace negotiations and instead called on the Taliban to continue
its <I
>jihad</I>. Against a backdrop of stalled negotiations, the temporary
seizure of the city of Kunduz by the Taliban in September&amp;ndash;October demonstrated
the deteriorating security situation in northern parts of the country and
the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s overarching resolve to continue the war. The capture of
Kunduz was considered the group&amp;rsquo;s most significant advance since being
forced out of power in 2001 and put an additional strain on Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s
relations with Pakistan, as Afghan leaders suspected Pakistani assistance
in the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s military operation in the north, although the Pakistani
Government denied this vehemently.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P63"
>Even as the Afghan Government continued
in its efforts to reinvigorate the peace process through multilateral initiatives
such as the Quadrilateral Co-ordination Group, which was established in January
2015 by Afghanistan, Pakistan, China and the USA to foster effective diplomatic
relations to promote Afghan peace and reconciliation, it achieved limited
progress, owing to the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s refusal to join the talks, citing non-fulfilment
of their fundamental demands&amp;mdash;namely the withdrawal of foreign forces,
the revocation of international sanctions on the group and the release of
its prisoners. The assassination of Taliban leader Mullah Mansour in a strike
by a US unmanned aerial vehicle (drone) in Balochistan, Pakistan, in May 2016
further undermined the peace process. Mansour's successor, Mullah Hibatullah
Akhundzada, chose to focus on consolidating his leadership and increasing
combat operations, instead of participating in the peace process. None the
less, a significant breakthrough was achieved by the Ghani Government when
it signed a peace agreement with Hekmatyar&amp;rsquo;s Hizb-i-Islami in September.
The agreement provided immunity from prosecution for the armed group&amp;rsquo;s
members for historic acts of violence and allowed its entry into the mainstream
political and military life of the country. In return, the group agreed to
recognize the Afghan Constitution and renounce militant activity outright.
In another significant step forward in the peace process, the Afghan Government
launched the Kabul Process for Peace and Security Cooperation in June 2017,
which aimed to consolidate regional and international peace initiatives under
Afghan leadership. The fact that the conference was convened as planned, even
in the face of intensified insurgent violence, was a testament to the resolve
of the political leadership to work towards lasting peace and stability in
Afghanistan.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Peace Process Reinvigorated</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P64"
>The year 2018 saw an increased momentum
in support of a peace process between the Government and the Taliban, bolstered
by calls for peace and security by various Afghan civil society groups as
well as religious communities. Although violence resumed eventually, the ceasefire
between government forces and the Taliban that began on 12 June 2018 to mark
the Islamic festival of Id al-Fitr was seen as another step in the right direction.
The appointment of US Special Representative for Afghan Reconciliation Zalmay
Khalilzad in September provided an additional impetus to Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s
pursuit of a negotiated settlement to the decades-old conflict. </P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P65"
>In an effort to demonstrate the seriousness
of its commitment to bring stability to Afghanistan, the USA had suspended
US&amp;nbsp;$2,000m. worth of security aid to Pakistan in January 2018, citing
repeated complaints of inaction on Pakistan's part in dismantling terrorist
sanctuaries within its borders, particularly those of the Taliban and the
group&amp;rsquo;s armed guerilla wing, the Haqqani network. In September the USA
revoked another $300m. in aid to Pakistan for the same reasons. Although the
decision was initially lauded by Afghans, who for long had held Pakistan responsible
as the festering ground for militancy in Afghanistan, the measure created
tensions in Pakistan&amp;rsquo;s relations with Afghanistan and the USA. The suspension
of aid was ultimately reversed by President Trump, upon a request from Pakistani
Prime Minister Imran Khan during a state visit to Washington, DC, in July
2019. Despite Trump&amp;rsquo;s original decision, which can be attributed to
his general unpredictability in foreign policy formulation, the significance
of Pakistan as a conduit for sending supplies to US troops stationed in Afghanistan
was undoubtedly already well known within the US Government. Furthermore,
it was widely believed that Pakistan would make for an important interlocutor
in future international peace talks with the Taliban, by virtue of it being
the only country with significant leverage over the group. Khalilzad occasionally
chose to ignore Ghani altogether while negotiating with the Taliban leadership
in Qatar. His main interlocuters, other than the Taliban representatives in
Doha, were Pakistani diplomats and generals, with the latter still presumably
retaining some influence on the Quetta Shura and senior Taliban leaders such
as Mullah Abdul Ghani Baradar. This side-lining of the Kabul regime not only
helped the Taliban in its re-emergence as an alternative political force,
it equally and even decisively weakened the Ghani regime and soon stories
about desertions by Afghan troops and civilian cadres began to make headlines
in the international media.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P66"
>Despite months of shuttle diplomacy
conducted by US Special Envoy Khalilzad between Kabul and the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s
representative office in Doha, as well as other countries in the region, and
several multilateral initiatives to promote dialogue on peace, the Taliban
remained adamant in its unwillingness to engage in direct talks with the Afghan
Government, which they considered a puppet of the USA. Negotiations between
Khalilzad and Taliban representatives continued in 2019, until President Trump
cancelled the talks scheduled for September, following a suicide bombing in
Kabul in which a US soldier was killed. Talks between the USA and the Taliban
resumed in December, but a significant reduction in violence over a specified
period was made a precondition for future negotiations to take place on a
political settlement. After intense negotiations, on 29 February 2020 the
USA and the Taliban signed the Agreement for Bringing Peace to Afghanistan.
Under the agreement, the USA pledged to reduce its troops in Afghanistan to
8,600 within 135 days of the deal being signed and to withdraw all troops
by mid-2021. The agreement also committed the Taliban to counter-terrorism
guarantees, including preventing the use of Afghan soil by any Afghan or foreign
militant group, particularly for the preparation of attacks against the USA
and its allies. As the Afghan Government was not party to the US-Taliban agreement,
it signed a separate Joint Declaration with the USA on the same day, which
reaffirmed the USA&amp;rsquo;s commitment to providing military and civilian support
to Afghanistan, in pursuance of mutual security objectives. The Declaration
also committed the Afghan Government to a number of relevant obligations that
were stipulated in the US-Taliban deal, which would pave the way for intra-Afghan
peace talks.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P67"
>Meanwhile, the protracted feud between
Ghani and Dr Abdullah continued. Dr Abdullah contested the declared result
of the September 2019 presidential election, as he had in 2014, and declared
himself to be President; the two political rivals held parallel swearing-in
ceremonies in March 2020, which was not only unusual, but also diminished
the credibility of the Afghan Government as a legitimate political entity.
Reviving the hopes of many, however, was the power-sharing deal eventually
signed between the two leaders in May, which signalled the formation of an
inclusive government, with Ghani as the President and Dr Abdullah as the Chairman
of the High Council for National Reconciliation, in charge of leading negotiations
with the Taliban and with the right to appoint one-half of the cabinet. Another
limitation to intra-Afghan talks was the lack of agreement between the Taliban
and the Afghan Government over two key issues: the Taliban refused to comply
with the Government&amp;rsquo;s demand for a comprehensive ceasefire, and the
Taliban&amp;rsquo;s precondition of releasing about 5,000 of its fighters from
Afghan prisons before commencing peace negotiations put the Government in
an invidious position. Further complicating the situation was the presence
of foreign Islamist militants in Afghanistan and an unwillingness on the part
of the Taliban to sever ties with many of them, rendering the concept of enduring
peace in the country a far-fetched proposition.</P></GEN-SECTION><GEN-SECTION
PRINT-STYLE="COLUMN"
SLLINK="SLSDOC"
SLSDOCRF="GEN-SECTREF"
><HEADING
>The Second Taliban Regime: Afghanistan at a Crossroads</HEADING><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P68"
>In the second half of the so-called
&amp;lsquo;transformational decade&amp;rsquo; (2015&amp;ndash;24), Afghanistan continues
to find itself confronted with serious challenges. The humanitarian crisis
in the country, induced by many years of conflict and low economic growth,
is deteriorating even further. The coronavirus disease (COVID-19) pandemic
has exacerbated the socioeconomic difficulties faced by the population, such
as extreme poverty, displacement, the repatriation of refugees from neighbouring
states and acute food insecurity. By May 2020 some 13.3m. people out of a
total population of almost 31m. were facing emergency levels of food insecurity,
with a total of about 3m. women and children suffering from acute malnourishment.
Just when the country was recovering from the devastation caused by the 2018
drought, the effects of which lingered into 2019, the pandemic, which spread
to Afghanistan in early 2020, pushed the already food-insecure Afghan people
into yet another crisis. The increasingly high number of undocumented returnees,
as well as documented returning refugees, coming mostly from Iran, also placed
a strain on the economy, with the Afghan Government incapable of providing
support to all. The fact that Iran was one of the countries worst hit by the
pandemic meant that many returning Afghans were potential carriers of the
virus. In any case, the general lack of contingency planning for health crises
and the limited capacity of the health care sector to operationalize preparedness,
owing to a consistent lack of funding, rendered Afghanistan particularly vulnerable
to the negative consequences of COVID-19.</P><P
ID="AFGHANISTAN.HISTORY.ED.DF.P69"
>Furthermore, of particular importance
is the country&amp;rsquo;s inability to venture down the path of economic self-reliance,
as the security climate and corresponding humanitarian crises still deem foreign
aid to be imperative for economic growth and development. Flows of aid, which
amounted to 100% of gross domestic product (GDP) in 2009, had fallen to 42%
of GDP by 2020, according to the World Bank, and the COVID-19 pandemic weighed
heavily on the Afghan economy, leading to a contraction of GDP of around 1.9%
in 2020, putting much of the population at risk of slipping into poverty.
An additional blow to the already weak economy was the consistently high level
of corruption among government officials, despite President Ghani&amp;rsquo;s
overt commitments to enact policies to tackle graft.</P><P
>Against this backdrop, the swiftly evolving security situation in 2021
had a dramatic impact on the country&amp;rsquo;s prospects. In anticipation of
intra-Afghan peace negotiations and as the US withdrawal of troops continued,
the Government released thousands of Taliban prisoners in 2020. The much awaited
peace talks began in Doha in September, with the Afghan government team headed
by Abdullah Abdullah and the Taliban team led by Mullah Abdul Ghani Baradar.
In the months that followed, despite assurances from both sides of their commitment
to a peaceful, negotiated resolution, little progress was made, the many expected
obstacles to agreement&amp;mdash;among them, the two groups&amp;rsquo; fundamentally
opposed visions of what a future Afghanistan, its rights, freedoms and values,
should look like&amp;mdash;seeming often insurmountable. There was also suspicion
among critics of the Taliban that the halting nature of the talks was attributable
to a wider strategy of buying time. Meanwhile, casualties mounted: according
to Abdullah, some 12,000 Afghans had died in the six months following the
signing of the Agreement for Bringing Peace to Afghanistan. With the pandemic
appearing to have dampened conflicts elsewhere, Afghanistan had the highest
number of civilian deaths from explosive devices in the world in 2020, according
to the charity Action on Armed Violence. Moreover, UNAMA noted a further rise
in violence following the commencement of the intra-Afghan talks and highlighted
a disturbing development: in 2020, 43% of civilian deaths were women and children.</P><P
>Further talks between the Afghan Government and the Taliban delegations
were held in Moscow, Russia, in March 2021. Regional actors such as China,
Russia and Pakistan, who were certain to play an important role after the
US withdrawal, reiterated pleas for a ceasefire. The lack of women&amp;mdash;predictably
absent from the Taliban team and in small numbers in the government team&amp;mdash;at
the negotiating table was cause for concern. Widespread doubt greeted the
Taliban&amp;rsquo;s repeated promises that it intended to respect women&amp;rsquo;s
rights, and first-hand accounts from areas under Taliban control, where punishment
for adultery or even rape was said to include flogging, appeared to contradict
its claims. A bomb attack at a girls&amp;rsquo; secondary school in a Kabul suburb
in May, which resulted in the deaths of more than 80 people, mainly girls,
was a reminder of what was at stake; the Taliban denied responsibility for
the bombing.</P><P
>The new US President, Joe Biden, extended the deadline for the withdrawal
of US troops from May to September (later brought forward to the end of August),
and the other NATO forces were to have departed by this time. Although many
had warned of likely Taliban gains, few were prepared for the astonishing
speed of the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s advances in mid-2021. By June it was said to
control one-quarter of the districts in Afghanistan, barring the urban centres,
and by July the Taliban had taken hold of more than one-half of the country,
although this was initially disputed by the Government. Many towns and cities
were effectively under siege, with Taliban forces controlling the surrounding
land and transport routes, and urban centres relying solely on air support.
Certain key border crossings with Iran, Pakistan and Tajikistan were also
rapidly taken over by the Taliban, making official control untenable. There
were reports of mass desertions and low morale among the Afghan forces. In
northern Afghanistan some 300 Afghan soldiers were said to have fled into
Tajikistan as the Taliban advanced, and many more followed. Meanwhile, the
decision of US forces to vacate Bagram airbase in the middle of the night,
neglecting to carry out a formal handover to Afghan forces, reportedly sparked
outrage in some quarters. US casualties during the long conflict amount to
2,448 deaths; the civilian death toll was many times this, having surpassed
100,000 in 2019, according to UNAMA, and it increased at an alarming rate
in 2021.</P><P
>Any uncertainty about the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s ability to capture and hold the
provincial capitals and larger urban centres was dispelled in August, when
their conquest of Zaranj in Nimroz province marked the beginning of the extraordinary
final phase of the group&amp;rsquo;s offensive. With heavy fighting in some areas
and apparently little resistance from the Afghan military in others, city
after city fell to the Taliban. Provincial capitals capitulated along with
strategic strongholds such as Kunduz, the site of the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s surrender
in 2001 and therefore a symbolic victory for the Taliban 20 years later. As
the onslaught continued and amid fears that Kabul itself could be captured
within months, the US Government announced the temporary deployment of 3,000
troops (later increased to 5,000) to secure the withdrawal of diplomatic staff
from the country. A full Taliban takeover appeared inevitable as it emerged
that Qandahar, Herat and Lashkar Gah had been captured soon after. A Taliban
spokesman assured the populace that no one would be harmed, but there were
reports of those linked to the Ghani administration and NATO forces being
targeted, and female workers and university students being told to stay at
home. Some 550,000 Afghans were said to have been displaced by the fighting
in 2021. In the event, the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s capture of Kabul on 15 August was
not marked by heavy fighting; President Ghani f<?Pub Caret?>led the country
and Taliban fighters were able to enter the presidential palace by the end
of the day, while the employees of numerous foreign embassies, along with
thousands of Afghans, sought refuge at Hamid Karzai International Airport.
On 16 August the Taliban declared that the war was over, and stated its commitment
to a peaceful transfer of power and the formation of a new government. To
this end, Hamid Karzai was reported to be heading a council of non-Taliban
Afghan leaders, including Abdullah Abdullah, negotiating with the Taliban.
The claims of the former Vice-President, Amrullah Saleh, that he was constitutionally
the Acting President, came to nothing. Ghani, who had relocated to the UAE,
in an interview claimed to have fled the country to avoid bloodshed, although
he expressed his intention eventually to return to Afghanistan. Ahmad Masoud&amp;rsquo;s
initial attempts to resist the Taliban in Panjshir did not succeed, and soon
the entire country was under Taliban control. Meanwhile, the focus of the
US, British and other foreign Governments turned to evacuating their citizens
from the country, using troops to secure the international airport and facilitating
evacuation through Pakistani cities. In addition, the US Administration froze
a large portion of the assets of Da Afghan Bank, the Afghan central bank,
to prevent the Taliban accessing billions of dollars of reserves held in US
accounts; this decision, which was repeatedly challenged by the Taliban as
the plight of ordinary Afghans became all the more desperate, seriously exacerbated
the country&amp;rsquo;s economic situation.</P><P
>The declaration in August of an Islamic Emirate of Afghanistan, with Hibatullah
Akhundzada as its Leader, was soon followed by the appointment of an interim
Government dominated by senior members of the Taliban. Mullah Mohammad Hassan
Akhund was named as acting Prime Minister and Mullah Baradar as one of three
acting Deputy Prime Ministers. Mullah Sirajuddin Haqqani, the leader of the
Haqqani network and subject of UN sanctions, became Minister of Interior Affairs
and Mullah Mohammad Yaqoob Mujahid, the son of Mullah Omar, was named as Minister
of Defence. Despite appeals from the international community, which continued
to withhold official recognition of the regime, the dramatic erosion of women&amp;rsquo;s
rights under the Taliban gathered pace, most notably in the restriction of
access to education and employment.</P><P
>Afghanistan was also on the brink of complete devastation, with the UN
estimating in January 2022 that around 24.4m. people, more than one-half of
the population, were in need of humanitarian assistance; Afghanistan had more
people in a state of emergency food insecurity than anywhere else in the world.
The sudden halt of development assistance following the Taliban takeover was
a defining factor, with drought and the effects of the COVID-19 pandemic contributing
to the crisis. The decision of US President Biden in February to sign an executive
order setting aside more than US $3,500m., or roughly one-half of the Afghan
Government&amp;rsquo;s assets frozen in the USA, for &amp;lsquo;ongoing litigation
by US victims of terrorism&amp;rsquo; was, needless to say, controversial, and
strongly condemned by the Taliban. The release of the remaining financial
assets, however, was under negotiation. By June 2022 some 25m. Afghans were
described by the UN as living in poverty, more than double the number in 2011.
An earthquake in that month deepened the country&amp;rsquo;s woes, causing an
estimated 770 deaths.</P><P
>Concerns about increased activity by the local branch of the militant Islamist
group Islamic State, the so-called Islamic State Khorasan, were not unfounded,
with the group claiming responsibility for numerous attacks in 2021 and 2022,
including a series of attacks on the Shi&amp;rsquo;a minority. In July 2022 al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
leader Ayman al-Zawahiri was killed by a US drone strike on his reported safe
house in Kabul, confirming the continuation of US engagement and intelligence-gathering
activities in Afghanistan. Certainly the apprehensions about disparate al-Qa&amp;lsquo;ida
militants gathering once again in the country and aligning themselves with
Islamic State or even some Taliban elements persisted in Western countries,
although in the immediate aftermath the Taliban refused to acknowledge the
presence or death of Osama Bin Laden&amp;rsquo;s deputy in their capital.</P><P
>The scale of the Taliban&amp;rsquo;s victory has raised many questions about
the past and the future: about the goals and failures of the lengthy US-led
occupation of Afghanistan, the extent of the international community&amp;rsquo;s
future involvement in the country and, of course, how the Taliban will ultimately
choose to govern. The potential for extremists and foreign militants to exploit
the current situation is also of grave concern. As the terrible human cost
of Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s many decades of conflict continues to mount, it appears
that the world&amp;rsquo;s attention has moved on and is, for now, focused elsewhere.
Nevertheless, Afghanistan&amp;rsquo;s continuing prominence as a geopolitical
and ideological battleground seems assured; perhaps more importantly, its
history contains crucial lessons for the global powers and the international
community. </P></GEN-SECTION></GEN-SECTION></COUNTRY-SURVEY>
